Bernie Sanders sent a formal letter to
the CEOs of Anthropic, Meta, and Open
Eye.
>> AI capabilities have reached a critical
threshold. Pause AI development.
>> The cat's out the bag. It's too late,
right?
>> Nvidia just [music] announced a
partnership that redefineses what GPU
compute means as a financial asset.
>> This is like the very first pitch of the
first inning of the buildout of the
Dyson swarm. Financial assets want
predictable depreciation and exponential
technologies don't give you predictable
depreciation.
>> I'm not as concerned that this will end
up being another mortgage back
securities fiasco for a few reasons. One
is Elon just dropped Grock 4.6 and he's
right. It's a banger. Grock 4.5 came out
2 weeks ago, 4.6 just this morning and
4.7 is rumored to be coming out in 2
weeks. 4.7, and this is what I think is
going to be really interesting, is going
to be trained on all the SpaceX physics
and engineering knowledge. You can't get
beyond Frontier with this stuff, but
what if you have the best engineers?
>> Now, that's a moonshot, ladies and
gentlemen.
>> Welcome back to Moonshots, everybody. Uh
we're going to be covering nine stories
today that span the frontier from
longevity, AI infrastructure, synthetic
biology, AI film making, urban air
mobility, and oh by the way, Gro 4.6 is
crushing it. The through line is the
same as always. You know, accelerating
singularity is compressing the distance
between the impossible and the
inevitable. We're back this week with
the moonshot quintet, uh AWG, our
in-house super intelligence. Alex,
welcome. Good to see you in your normal
apartment. Good to be super intelligent.
>> You are my friend Dave Blondon, our
investor and AI extraordinaire.
>> I was over at MIT all day today, hence
the garb, but uh our Techre teams just
got back from SF and they brought back
huge amounts of knowledge and they're
all over at MIT sale dispersing it
across the campus right now.
>> Love it. And Salem Ismael, our
empressario of exponential
organizations. See, where are you today?
Still in Toronto? I'm still in Toronto
heading back tomorrow.
>> Okay.
>> I should be going back now, but this
podcast happened and I can't fly, you
know, within like six hours of
[laughter]
>> We're going to we're going to put a
Starlink on your on your hat and have
you walk around with it. Uh, and back by
popular demand, Immad Mustach, the
embodiment of the intelligent internet.
Immad, I hope you're reading the
comments on the last pod uh that we did
together. People are loving you. Have
you seen them?
>> Uh, yeah. I did see some of them. I
don't normally read the comments. I made
an exception and it's very kind what
everyone said. It's great being amongst
you guys.
>> It is. It is. It works for my American
wife. It works for the others. You know,
[laughter]
>> I'm Peter D. Madness, your host, your
optimism amplifier. Please remember that
having an optimistic and abundance
mindset is a choice. And our mission
here is to deliver datadriven optimism
that helps you make that choice. So
guys, uh, last night I was in Utah, the
University of Utah. It was the finals
for the $101 million longevity or shall
I say Healthspan X-P prize. Super
psyched. We awarded a million dollars to
10 teams, recognized another 10
finalists. This is on the march to
winning the $80 million grand prize.
We've given away 20 million so far. And
the mission of these teams and you know
everybody please get excited about this
is to add 20 healthy years on your life.
Asking teams to reverse your functional
losses that we get through aging in
cognition give you the ability to think
and have memory like you did 20 years
ago in muscle the ability to build
muscle like you did 20 years ago and in
your immune system. Uh and it's
extraordinary. We had 800 teams enter
this competition. every possible
approach from mitochondria to uh you
know stem cells to you know gene editing
it's it's extraordinary so this is a
competition that will be won by 2030 so
keep an eye on this uh you know sele I
don't know if you want to jump in on
this one
>> you 20 20 is infinity right
>> I mean you know I think there's there's
the
X-prise was such a huge inspiration when
I was writing the exo book because
you're reaching outside
and I mean 800 teams is that I think
that's a record for the traditional
prizes for us, right?
>> It's kind of an incredible thing.
>> Elon's Elon's $und00 million prize for
carbon removal ended up with something
like 1500 teams. But, you know,
reversing aging, it's got to be tougher.
And by the way, the teams here don't do
this in theory. They don't do this in
mice. They have to actually do human
trials. So, they're all going to be
doing trials with control groups and and
humans, uh, probably around 150 people
in the trial. So, it's real data and
we're going to actually know which of
these 20 to 30 approaches that actually
make it to the finals work. Uh, and for
me, you know, Alex, we've been talking
about being in the midst of longevity
escape velocity. This is accelerating
it. It's going to be spiky. I think I I
still think just as with AGI either in
our rearview mirror as I think or some
might say it's either here or almost
here. I I do still expect that health
span and longevity escape velocity it's
going to be spiky and and I'm just
optimistic that we can even out the
spikes even if there's a sub population
that achieves health span on the margin
a few years before everyone else. You
know, one of the most important things I
think about this competition when we
launched the $10 million Ansari X-P
prize for spaceflight back in 1996, you
know, back then people did not believe
in commercial space flight. They didn't
believe that individual teams could do
this and carry humans compared to the
government. And as it progressed the
confidence level in this and then when
it was won money flowed in regulations
changed you know Bezos and Musk started
uh you know Blue Origin and SpaceX and
it be changed the game. So I'm feeling
the same thing going on right now. You
know longevity the idea of reversing
aging has been sort of a a crackpot idea
for most of the last few decades while
I've been in the industry and it's
beginning to change. People are starting
to believe yes, it's going to happen.
Yes, we're in this health span
revolution.
>> We're getting to a we're getting to a
when, not an if question, right? And
that's really huge. I I wanted to point
out something that was that's really
important here, Peter. When you launched
the Ansari X-P prize,
>> there was no space industry to speak of,
at least in the commercial side, and now
we have a trillion dollar industry that
did not exist, right? Because the
collective innovation plus all the
members of all the teams end up going to
SpaceX, Blue Origin, etc., etc. And we
could expect the same thing to happen
here where you end up with essentially
you're creating a $101 million bet.
You're building a portfolio of
experiments and allocating capital to
wherever there's demonstrated results.
It's an unbelievable model that we've
now seen repeat over and over again.
It's incredibly exciting to see.
>> Yeah. I was
>> question for you Peter on this one. I I
always ask the counterfactual question.
Is is there something having now run
this health span prize or at least the
the beginnings of it? Do you think that
if this prize had been created say 20 or
30 years ago that we could have made on
margin enormous progress or do you think
there's some historic contingency that
means right now is really the the first
time in history where we could make
credible progress on it?
>> Yeah, I I think we had a lot of
comments. We had a lot of the top
scientists, Aubrey Deg Grrey was there
last night who coined the term longevity
scape velocity and then and then Ray
popularized it. Uh I think everybody was
at the consensus that the timing is
perfect that the tools for genome
sequencing for uh you know making
specific molecules for being able to
measure uh and and report with AI uh are
the tools that are required today. I
mean there might have been some
approaches uh that could have been done
20 years ago but I think today uh is
when we're going to make the greatest
progress uh and I'm starting to see you
know capital flowing in aggressively at
the end of the day longevity is going to
be the biggest market right if you could
add 30 you know I've had this
conversation you know See probably you
have as well on stage you know with YPO
audiences or family offices and I say
how much of your wealth would you spend
been for an extra 30 years of life. The
honest answer is nearly all of it.
Right.
>> Yeah. I mean you and and the powerful
distinction there's not so much lifespan
but the health span effects are really
really powerful.
>> Yeah. The numbers today are for the
United States if you if you look at it
uh basically uh 100 years ago in 1900
the average life expectancy was 47.
Today it's 79. We added about two months
per year over the last century. And
today, while the lifespan is 79, you're
healthy until average age 63. And you
spend the last 19 years of your 16 years
of your life in poor health. And so when
I was with talking to Katios about this,
I said, listen, the biggest benefit the
US budget could have and the US economy
could have is add 20 healthy years in
people's lives. they they're retiring uh
later. Uh they're not spending as much
government money on on you know sick
care. So it could be a huge
transformation. Alex
>> Yeah. I maybe just again coming back to
this historic counterfactual. I one of
the things that irks me the most is that
so many of the abundanceoriented futures
that we want to find ourselves in like
LEV the super intelligence solve
everything just take forever. Uh and I I
do wonder again we're is it 20 years
post Yamanaka that like Yamanaka I think
was 2006 we're in 2026. What did we blow
these 20 years on? Why couldn't we have
done this 10, 20, 30 years ago?
>> I got a question for you, Alex.
>> I'll answer that.
>> That I think when you get multiple
exponential technologies that can
address a particular space, then that's
the point to in invest or put up a prize
because then you get radical outcomes at
very low cost. And so maybe there's a
benchmark of the minute some domain has
two or three or more exponential
technologies converging on it, that's
the point to have put dollars into
something like this. [clears throat]
>> Dave,
>> well, there's no doubt in my mind that
I'm going to do more productive work in
the second half of 2026 than in my
entire life combined up till 2026. So
throw it back at you, Alex. Like even if
we had worked really hard on this 20
years ago, uh would anything that we did
between then and today even hold a
candle to what we'll achieve between now
and the end of the year? Cuz I mean it's
so funny to me, you know, my my
daughter's over at Madna. She's a
biochemical engineer and she listens to
the pod of course you know and it's so
obvious to her that we're in an AGI hard
takeoff now and the people she works
with in biotech are about 1% AI aware
and 99% not aware but the AI aware now
people are spending over half their day
maybe 80 90% of their day talking to AI
agents and not in meetings and not you
know running gels and not running assays
because it's it's just a different mode
of living that's accelerating
tremendously, but the the aware subset
is tiny.
>> I I almost think I think it's an
important point and I almost think we
need a new term for it. I I just
thinking off the cuff maybe like
retrospective hyperdelation, this very
singularityoriented idea that with super
intelligence you discover that
everything that you spent the past
decades on was just a total waste and
you should have instead just done
nothing, twiddled your thumb for
decades, waited for super intelligence
to solve it for you
>> or or just work on, you know, chip fabs
or something that will, you know,
they'll be very useful on that day or in
Texas or
>> all these people like who who spent
six-year PhDs trying to divine protein
structures just mostly wasted.
>> Well, that one was was really outed by
Demis. Yeah, I mean that one what it was
like an average of four years to
discover one fold.
>> I I knew there was a reason I didn't do
a graduate degree. That was it.
[laughter] It would have been
irrelevant. This was your post
justification.
>> That's right.
This
>> I mean it it could be worse. You could
be a pure mathematician, right?
>> [laughter]
>> Like
>> they're all cooked too. They're they're
having this the same moment of on week.
>> Yeah. But at least with the biologists,
the longevity people, you can do assays
and things physically. No, look, I think
that this is the biggest market in the
world as you said, but it's the first
time that it's tractable. I think if you
go back to when there were the Yamanaka
factors, all these other things, you
didn't have the infrastructure necessary
and the talent pool necessary.
>> [snorts]
>> I think that as you've seen the various
breakthroughs in other things and
everything come together right now there
will be a shortage of people that can
really work on longevity properly even
though it is the biggest market in the
world and 10 years ago 20 years ago that
would have been even tinier there are
only a few people actually looking at
some of these things back at that time
so I think it is this confluence factor
all coming together and like I said it's
finally tractable so the people who are
winning in the longevity x prize any
indication that those things will work
and I don't think they'll be short of
capital but again the X-P prize is the
catalyst right and that was the whole
idea
>> you know Peter you've pointed out
something that I think is incredibly
important to highlight right which is
that we spend today huge amounts of
money on treating chronic diseases at
the end of
>> you know what the number is sim it's the
global cost of age related disease is 20
trillion per year globally
>> crap
>> yeah it's a huge
>> Daniel Craft used like 85% of healthcare
costs for the last 5 years of your life
type thing. This is a staggering number,
right? Because now
>> just for context, glo the global economy
is 120 130 trillion total. 20 trillion
of that is
>> look at that number, right? So now now
the business model becomes how do you
maintain uh decent function, bodily
function before the dis disease appears
and it'll completely change healthcare
economics. Massive impact
>> and and global economics in general,
>> global economics
>> in terms of productivity and wasted
capital. Well, I think this is this is
where the peptides have come really
interesting, right? Like it was like to
lose weight, you had to work out. I'm
about to start, you know, get rid of
that extra report in on the pod.
>> I'm going to get it report in and see
how my weight loss goes. But the thing
is,
>> which peptides am you taking? Do tell.
>> I was going to try the one
>> randomide.
Yeah,
>> I'm on retroide.
>> But I know I'm going to lose weight,
right? Are you getting access to No, but
serious. Okay. Has it even Oh, you're in
Canada.
>> No, no, I'm not in Canada. I get it in
the US. It's totally
>> Yeah, they're drug dealers out there.
[laughter] Black market
>> drug peptide dealers, right? There we
go.
>> I guess See, that'll just be our little
secret. There's no one paying attention
to
>> here. Nobody's listening.
>> But but this is how like you know that
you're going to lose weight with it,
right? And that's the first. And so now
the concept of you can take a pill or an
intervention and you could live longer.
Well, you're already losing weight like
that. And so I think again that's a big
awareness that's caused the longevity
market to get even bigger.
>> Yeah. GLP1s are the first longevity drug
uh you know in a lot of people's
opinions and it's one of the biggest
grossing drugs if not the largest one in
human history. I I've gone even further
that than that just again bit of back of
the envelope calculations suggesting and
again this is not medical advice uh that
GLP1s especially third and maybe fourth
generation GLP1s may actually be when I
refer to LEV longevity escape velocity
as being potentially spiky a pretty big
spike there there have been studies done
recently on uh some of the third
generation if memory serves GLP1s that
suggest uh and again not medical advice
that we may be or at least some subop of
humans that have undergone GLP-1 studies
may be at something like 70% LEV just
with GLP-1 therapy. So if if that is the
case and again encourage folks to to do
their own uh independent back of the
envelope analysis that's a heck of a an
LEV spike in a subop that's being
administered GLP1s.
>> Yeah. Anyway, watch this space
everybody. It's exciting.
>> Peter, I've got one more question for
you. Please um as you looked at the
finalists cuz I couldn't make it to the
finals but we've been tracking some of
the teams etc. You you had a great
snapshot view are you in the view that
lev we get to it by 2030 or earlier. Uh
so here's the idea right if any of these
teams win and can reverse your
functional age right this is not a
number from a you know uh a particular
blood test you take you know that
changes on the back of a form this is
are you feeling functionally younger are
you know do you have better muscle
building capability better memory better
immune system so what really matters is
your function and so if we can do that
if we can actually reverse the clock by
20 years of function, then you get to
enjoy the next 20 years of
breakthroughs. And if you don't believe
we're going to have incredible
breakthroughs over the next 20 years,
you know, basically, you know, wholesale
simulators and AI, you know, the impact
of quantum, whatever that might be in in
in cell biology and understanding how we
age, uh, then you're missing the boat.
Your goal is to keep in the best health
right now, which means what? Sleep eight
hours. Unless you're E-mod and Alex
probably don't sleep more than four
hours, but you're short sleepers.
>> But you're short sleepers. Sleep as much
as you need to.
>> So, I'll make a comment here which I've
made before, which is that,
>> you know, the business model of religion
is to sell heaven. As we have life
extension coming, how are you going to
sell heaven if people aren't dying? So,
this breakthrough will mean that
religion is cooked. we [laughter] have
forever to figure it out. Like
>> uh there will still be a lot of
religions doing very well uh from people
tithing. But again, I guess the advice
right now is do what you can to keep in
the best health. Don't die from
something stupid. It's sleep, exercise,
you know, proper diet and mindset.
Mindset so important. You know, I think
my greatest attribute is my longevity
mindset. So take it on. We'll keep on
reporting in the space. It's an
important part. This episode is
sponsored by Google for startups. Think
about this for a second. You now have
access to the same generative AI models
that cost hundreds of millions of
dollars to train. Google's startup
tactical guide for generative media
gives you complete blueprint for
deploying Google Deep Minds models in
production. Images, video, audio, all of
it. Real architecture, real results.
Find the link in the show notes below.
But let's move us on. Um these were a
couple of stories Immod that you shared
with me. Um these are three stories that
landed this week together that describe
really I think the collapse of Hollywood
economics and the rise of something much
bigger. So our first story is a company
called Higsfield that just made a a
movie called Cully Hill Boys. It's
110minute feature film. The first
fulllength AI generated movie with
licensed celebrity likenesses. Here are
the numbers. Uh the total budget for
this film roughly you know fulllength
film $2 million team size 28 people
production time four weeks compute cost
$1 million uh they use Cance 2.5 as the
generation and they open sourced all 10
steps in their workflow so anyone can
replicate it so here's the context right
uh a feature film with celebrity talent
today costs between 20 million and 100
million if you're not using AI and it
takes you know, a year to 18 months.
Hicksfield did it for 2% of the cost and
6% of the time. So, I want to share a
short video, a little clip from
Hicksfield so we can appreciate it.
Is that
spices?
>> Supposed to be over2 million pounds
packed in this little nut.
Who smuggles coriander in aing boat?
Someone who suspects it might get
nipped. Or
where'd your boys go after you left the
pier?
What the is that supposed to mean? We
came here and waited for youing pricks
like we wereing told.
>> Let's go through it step by step, shall
we?
>> All right. Uh, our second story, uh,
Bloomberg reported that nine out of the
top 10 texttovideo models on AI analysis
leaderboard are coming from China. Uh,
this is a headline, but the real story
is deeper and I'm curious what you guys
think about this. You know, Hollywood
forever has been the dominant producers
of films and it's basically exporting US
culture to the rest of the world. What
happens when the world is flooded by
Chinese-prouced English-speaking films?
How is that swaying public interests and
public points of view? Uh and the second
thing is that these Chinese models that
are dominating video uh generation are
also learning physics, motion, object
permanence and causality which is what's
needed for robotics and autonomous
driving. So things are moving quickly
there. The third one very quickly then
we'll go into the discussion here. a
model called LTX 2.5 is the newest
version of the most popular open source
state-of-the-art video generation model
and it works on your your MacBook Pro
which is extraordinary. So, uh I want
you to imagine uh something that allows
the individual uh to sort of tee up and
produce their own movie. Uh one more
clip. This is from LTX 2.5.
This is LTX, the most downloaded open-
source world model. And today, [music]
it just got better. Introducing LTX 2.5.
And now with the Fusion Fidelity
Rendering, a new way to generate video.
Instead of locking every scene to one
compression rate, our model allocates
compute by scene complexity and budget,
rendering flawless detail where it
matters, efficient everywhere else. It
generates fast enough to run live inside
a game or a simulation or power a live
avatar and real-time products are
already earning off worlds built on it.
>> So gentlemen, let's go to you first,
Iman. This has been your world for the
better part of a decade.
>> Yeah, it's um happening right on
forecast realtime highdefinition video.
Um, so LTX can generate a 10-second clip
in 7 seconds at that quality that you
just saw, which is indistinguishable.
And a few years ago when we had the
state of the art model, it was not like
that. It was like slow moving, you know,
like Will Smith eating spaghetti was
awful and horrible.
>> Now you can do a spaghetti eating Will
Smith, right? And it'll just do it
instantly on your local kind of laptop.
So you said kind of the disruption of
Hollywood like you never need to reshoot
a scene now with the flows that you
have. People are licensing their things
and as you said Hicksfield released an
80page guide because they're a company
that allows you to make movies on
exactly how they made the movie like
it's almost open sourced. Uh Hicksfield
got from it's an ex Snap uh leader from
Snapchat. It's 700 million revenue run
rate right now in about one and a half
years to give the idea of kind of how
much uptake. But that's just the start.
>> That's crazy.
>> Crazy number.
>> Yeah, cuz every pixel will be rendered.
Like if you see reactor who are using
LTX now, like again it could be that
Alex might be a simulation already, but
for the rest of us, you know, we could
put our avatars live in the next month
or two at a level that you won't be able
to tell.
>> Walk us through the one the $1 million
budget to make a one and a half compute
budget to make a one and a half hour
long movie. What will that be by
September 25th by the time we have the
Moonshots live event?
>> So it depends on the level of quality.
Seance 2.5 is the best model. It's a
large big model that costs about $3 per
30 seconds roughly, but you need lots of
shots and it can have 50 inputs of audio
and video and things. The cheaper models
are 10 20 times cheaper, but like 90% of
the quality. So, it all depends on
exactly how you're shooting and the type
of shots cuz Seance can do 30 second
clips, but the average movie on the
Hollywood box office right now is 3
seconds per shot. Wow.
>> So you could have a 10 times reduction
in cost. You could shoot a movie just
like that one probably for a 100,000 of
compute and then 10,000 of compute
>> probably by the new year.
>> This is what we saw in our uh you know
foundations of AI ventures class at MIT
is that it went from PowerPoint demos to
full functioning products in one year.
Like to to be competitive on demo day
now you have to actually build the
entire product. But I I suspect the
movie like our our target for September
25th is bring a script.
>> Well, the So Dave's referring to the
Future Vision X-P prize that we're going
to be awarding with all the mates here
at Moonshots Live and you go to
moonshots.com to learn more. We have
5,000 entries PE 5,000 who are creating
three minute threeminut trailers and a
film treatment. I just had a meeting
this morning with the team at Range
Media and Google to down select and
we'll down select to ultimately the top
100, 50, 25, 10. The top five will be at
uh at Moon at Moonshots Live on the
25th. And everyone listening, we're
going to you can come and be there live
and vote live. We're going to also have
a live stream of the event. But yeah,
it's and we're going to do this year on
year. So every year it's going to get
better, cheaper for sure. I think this
is going to be much bigger than we
originally envisioned. I mean, I know
it's a big vision to start with, but you
we were thinking, okay, then it'll be a
$20 million, you know, year-long
endeavor to turn it into a real
featurelength film, but in reality,
you're going to unleash the creativity
of 5,000 people who almost all can make
their movie within a year,
>> 100%. We have a $10 million budget to
make the winner's film between the money
we're awarding and uh and foreign film
rights. But I was just talking with
Range. Well, we're going to be having
five finalists who will crown the winner
and you should see the trophy. It's
beautiful. Um, uh, they want to make all
five. So, we want to create an engine
here. Uh, Salem, what do you think the
implications of this are? And then,
Alex, I'd love your thoughts as well.
>> Well, you know, there there's I'll go at
it from a exo perspective. when you we
actually talked about Hollywood as one
of the first uh domains that went into
an exponential organizations model
because what happened when you broke up
the Hollywood studios in the 50s and 60s
is Hollywood turned into a a cluster of
external resources where you'd produ
movie production would start and
essentially a swarm of people would
appear grips and camera people and
actors and editors and whatever and
they'd get together for that project and
they completely disband after that,
right? And we see the beginnings of that
in in Silicon Valley now. Uh and so that
was that first wave of Hollywood
becoming an exponential organization.
Everything was assets on de demand.
Everything was staff on demand. But now
when you have everything being driven by
AI goes through the organizational
singularity and essentially it's compute
cost now moving closer and closer to
what Alex always talks about. You have
domain collapse now. uh coming along and
so that's going to completely change the
game again for this. So you've gone
through two big waves in in Hollywood,
the second one just starting now.
>> Alex, what are you excited about here?
What are your thoughts?
>> So I made myself watch The Cully Hill
Boys and I I must say just as a
preliminary
>> I I skimmed through the whole thing
watching a good chunk of it.
>> See, when you only sleep two hours a
night, you can just do that. Yeah.
>> So I had I I had to watch this. Um, so
it's it's it's not my favorite genre. I
would characterize Cully Hill Boys as
sort of British Bollywood. Uh, not quite
even sure what genre this is. It seems
to be, as far as I can tell, about the
hijinks of a bunch of British rappers
that get into all sorts of trouble.
Contentwise,
not super interesting to me, but at the
functional level, it is really
interesting. And there were multiple
times in the movie where I had to wonder
were the generative actors, so the
likenesses were based on real humans,
but were the scenes that were being
generated given the complexity of the
interpersonal dynamics such as they were
in this movie, were was there some sort
of emergent theory of mind that was
almost necessary in order to generate
some of these scenes with people
interacting with each other? and
especially generative violence. There
were multiple times, you know, people
with knives chopping things, chopping
meat, uh, threatening other people where
I had to wonder I is is at at some level
we talk about AI personhood on this pod
from time to time is is there in in some
sense at at some presumably intermediate
layer in a diffusion transformer
somewhere deep in the bowels of
Higsfield, is there some diffusion
transformer or similar model that felt
threatened uh at some point in in terms
of these generative violence scenes. So
that that was my take on the content of
the movie. Moving to
>> you were worried that the residual AI
might have been threatened in the making
of the movie.
>> Correct.
>> I'm talking my head about that.
>> Okay.
No, no natural persons harmed obviously
in in the generation of this, but I I do
wonder
>> we're going to have an a disclaimer on
on content. No AI was harmed in the
making of this or
>> traumatized of this or traumatized. I
mean,
>> so so I I I do worry parathetically
about that. The bigger question on the
economics of this, I think, is at what
point do generative video capabilities
start to reconverge with the anthropic
school, which I'd characterize as a
token revenue maxing. Right now, it
seems pretty clear that if you're using
sea dance models, it doesn't matter how
many millions of dollars of X vision
prize money are going to shower down on
folks who can create spiffy videos about
the future. That's nowhere close to the
amount of money that one can earn in
principle with revenue per token maxing.
And right now, these appear to be two
separate lines of effort. On the one
hand, we have a vibrant largely Chinese
dominated at the training side consumer
economy for generating consumer videos.
And on the other hand, we have
enterprise revenue per token unit value
maxing that seems to be largely going to
codegen and enterprise problems. And
right now, these are largely two
distinguishable ways to burn tokens or
diffusion transformer equivalents of
tokens, flops. Two different ways to
burn flops. One of them maximizes
revenue, one of them maybe maximizes
consumer engagement and wow factor, but
they're they're nonetheless separate. I
don't think they're likely to remain
separate that much longer. And the
reason is so I use Fable every day and I
I use its competitors every day. And I I
will say the strongest models,
[clears throat] the models that are
strongest at revenue per token value
maxing are just still terribly weak at
modeling the the visual dynamics of the
world. I don't want to call it physics
because it's not physics, although a lot
of people call it physics. It's at best
classical mechanics. But like the the
the intuitive the physical intuition
from general purpose video generation
requires that you at least have some
embodied intuition. And right now, Fable
and its peers are just incredibly weak
at that. And I think in order to
ultimately revenue max per unit token,
it's going to require that these
Fable-esque models have just amazing
visual intuition as well. And we'll
finally see a convergence or
reconvergence of these two lines.
>> Yeah. One of my hot takes on this is,
you know, are we going to see the
primary actors out there, the Matt
Damon's or the uh, you know, Leonardo
DiCaprio licensing their likeness? And I
think not, but there are so many
lookalikes out there. So, you know, the
the the producer is going to go and say,
"No, that's not Mike Matt Damon. That's
John Smith and he looks like Matt Damon
and we licensed him and he's in this
movie."
>> Right? And I think that's a it's going
to happen. That's going to be the
workaround on getting, you know, the
actors you know and love uh into this
and there's nothing they can do about
it. There there's an alternative which
is that we're already seeing which is
dead actors. So dead actors who can't
record any new movies. Their estates are
highly incentivized to license away
their likeness for this purpose. So I
think dead actors like maybe we'll see a
an equivalent of SAG pop up just for
dead actors. Uh and they'll be the most
profitable actors in Hollywood. Dead
actors. I I think that's likely to
happen. How much do you think people
will if you can make like a near Matt
Damon, you know, very similar character
but obviously not him or you have the
actual Matt Damon, how much will people
care in in terms of Baka?
>> I don't think they're going to care.
They, you know, cuz you don't care what
the person's named in the movie. You
just like that actor. That actor brings
you good feelings from previous, you
know, engagements.
>> Yeah. I think that you also seeing the
rise of AI stars now as well. They're
winning deals. And I have actually had
this discussion with various film stars
where they've been like that SAG Afro
deal has massive holes in it. 80% of me
plus 20% of my character can be licensed
by the studio. You know, like where does
the person stop and the character start
because obviously they have the
character rights and things like that.
The other thing I'd like to say actually
one thing I found very interesting is as
we were doing um some of the more
interesting frontier work one of the
things we found very useful is to get
the AI models to generate images and
visualize what they're doing using
something like GPT image.
>> So even if you're doing
>> what does that mean? So if you're if
you're doing like SEM is doing an
organizational paper for example on
exponential organizations, it's doing
text text text and then you tell it to
generate a visual of everything that
it's done and analyze it in any way that
it wants and it almost moves it to
another frame of reference
>> cuz it's pulling in from this visual
cortex kind of thing. And then you could
tell it to expand and collapse it and
you get these really weird images
sometimes. But you can see actually it's
exploring different parts. So I think
we've seen that actually work for some
very interesting things and I think it
fits with what Alex said as all these
models come together to create value as
it were.
>> I'm excited about interactive movies,
right? If you can generate faster than
you can view it, then you can have a
movie that's actually that's actually
measuring your emotions and changing as
you're viewing it, which I I find
>> Peter is what we're seeing. I mean
they're they're popularly branded world
models even though they're really just
interactive videogen models. That that
is what we're seeing.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So that's what the LTX model is
right now.
>> So that was the first model that could
do it at high definition. And then when
that's combined with frame generation on
the latest graphics cards, what you've
just described like before it was world
models playing like blocky video games.
Now you can have interactive Elden Ring
or whatever you want as of like this
week.
>> Yeah. And I you said something you might
you said something a few podcasts ago
that we're going to end up with a world
or Frontier model running on a MacBook
Air. I mean this is a very specific use
case. Are we on track for that like cuz
we've got this thing running on a
MacBook Air. Well, yeah. So again, it
was it's very slow to generate, you
know, like a few tokens a second. But
now you are getting to the point where
frontier level models are coming here.
But video frontier models are like 20
billion parameters yet they understand
all this. They can generate in 2K. Uh
language and the code models are
obviously a lot bigger. Although you're
about to have the new Quen dropping in a
couple of days, but I think it's all
going in one direction because we're
optimizing the heck out of these things.
And ultimately what a model is is it's
an input data distribution that gets
compiled into weights and the data going
into these models is getting better and
better and better. Awesome.
>> We had the whole uh State Street
executive team here yesterday here in
the studio and we took them through the
holiday and word to the wise the holiday
you know Ember who is the AI just starts
talking to you says you can build any
movie any song any code what do you want
to do and it's way too open-ended and
then the the answer you get back is I
don't know a hip-hop song with no words
like [laughter] okay so you need to
actually create the virtual environment
the movie scene
and draw the user in and then have them
guide the movie in the direction they
want to go. But just having it like, you
know, autogenerate off your thoughts is
just too is too free form. People just
don't know how to even
>> freeze up.
>> Freeze up. Yeah.
>> Maybe just a closing thought on this
one. Peter, I I do think the recent
launch of Opus 5 is a step in the right
direction to seeing a convergence
between call it frontier models on the
one hand and videogen or world models on
the other because it I think we we
talked on the pod a bit about how Opus 5
seemed almost mildly benchmaxed towards
front-end development and the the loop
between visuals and code. I I think I I
I interpret and I construe that as the
early signs that anthropic probably
other labs as well are feeling economic
pressure to produce models that do an
absolutely amazing job of visually
reflecting on their own chain of thought
that when they produce say a website
that they then do a visual analysis of
their their website that feeds back into
their chain of thought and they do a
multimodal reasoning over their own
visual outputs and that ultimately say
In the next few months, as the ability
to produce what used to be considered
AAA level video games becomes standard
fair for what people expect from the
Frontier models, that will be the
ultimate forcing function for say
forcing anthropic type Frontier models
to have just absolutely amazing visual
capabilities. Even if anthropic can't be
bothered to produce like direct videogen
capabilities, even if it can indirectly
reproduce Counterstrike.
>> All right. Yeah, that's why they that's
why they had claw of duty. People were
making call of duty of duty.
>> Exactly.
>> Our next story is one that both EMOD and
AWG texted me this morning. Uh Elon just
dropped Grock 4.6 and he's right. It's a
banger. XAI's latest model matches GPT
5.6 Six saw on the artificial analysis
intelligence index at 61. Tying for
frontier level performance at $2 and $6
per million tokens input and output. The
focus this time is longunning agents.
Grock 4.6 stays with complex tasks
across many steps. Whether researching,
coding, analyzing, or turning a broad
product idea into a working first
version. It self- tests and verifies its
own work before moving on. It's
available today in cursor and Grock
build. The model cadence is crazy,
right? So 4.5, you know, Grock 4.5 came
out 2 weeks ago, 4.6 just this morning,
and 4.7 is rumored to be coming out in
two weeks. Uh, incredible gentlemen. Uh,
Alex, over to you first.
>> Yeah. So, I want to give Elon applause
and I want to at the same time
>> you've been you've been merciless on on
XAI for the last few pods.
>> I I wouldn't characterize myself as
merciless. I I think [laughter] my my my
job here is okay.
>> My my job is to call balls and strikes
as I see them without favor or
prejudice. Uh that that's how I see it.
So So I I view and again I I I lack
insider information, but I I view Grock
4.6 6 as essentially the next version of
cursor. Uh so XAI, SpaceXI, and Elon
have been quite public about how 4.6
leaned heavily on post-training thanks
to the Cursor acquisition, which I think
is still in the process as we're as
we're recording this, of being
completed. But history rhymes quite a
bit. We've spoken in recent pods about
what the Chinese Frontier Labs are doing
and how they're allegedly distilling on
mass reasoning traces from Claude and
other Western models. And in some sense,
I I again this is an outsers's
perspective. I I view SpaceX's
acquisition and even prior to the
consummation, the the final consummation
of the acquisition, their licensing of
all of the reasoning trace data from
Cursor as essentially pulling a
westernized version of what the Chinese
Frontier Labs were doing, which is to
say siphoning off reasoning traces from
lots of people historically interacting
via cursor with Claude and Claude's
competitors and then using that
incredibly valuable reasoning trace data
to do post-tra training on their models.
And I I think now that we're in the the
reasoning model era, we're a couple
years in at this point. It's those
reasoning traces for mid-training and
post-training that are just so essential
in in in terms of catching up to the
frontier. They won't get you past the
frontier. So, it it's sort of like a
onetrick pony in terms of nearly
catching up, but it's a heck of a
one-trick pony. The other thing Elon has
going for him that the Chinese Frontier
Labs don't is he has the compute. He has
the Nvidia GPUs and he has soon his own
Dyson swarm with the Nvidia GPUs that
all of the Chinese frontier labs that
are pulling the same trick with
siphoning off allegedly Western
reasoning traces in order to do their
own post-raining and their own
distillation don't have. So the the
bullc case for the Elon strategy is he
gets the algorithmic insights to just
catch up to the frontier from the cursor
reasoning traces and he gets the compute
advantage that the Chinese labs don't
have. I think the question is not can
Grock 4.6 and its successors catch up to
the frontier. Seems like they can
because they have access or the near
frontier uh to the extent they have the
reasoning traces. It's can they leaprog
the frontier and achieve
state-of-the-art performance.
>> What do you think about that? Can they
Uh yeah, I think they definitely can. Uh
I think we were discussing before and
Elon's come out and said it publicly
now. He thinks 4.7 will go above Opus.
So it'll take number one in a couple of
weeks. And right now you had 1.5
trillion parameters for um 4.5 that was
then post-trained to 4.6 six. Just like
cursor originally took Kimmy K2 and
post-trained it with three times the
amount of compute that was used to
pre-train Kimmy K2 to almost top level
coding performance. The next model is
going from 1.5 to 2 trillion parameters.
That's uh 4.7. But five is coming in at
6 and then 10 trillion parameters. So
it's going to be worring away. And just
through scale and just through the
quality of the post- trainining data, it
should achieve the frontier. But the
question is, is it going to be useful?
You know, do you have that kind of
knowledge there in the basic everyday
stuff which we're seeing with bot and
things like that now coming out from
them. And then the more advanced stuff
because 4.7 and this is what I think is
going to be really interesting is going
to be trained on all the SpaceX physics
and engineering knowledge.
And that's going to be the real test. As
Alex said, like you can't get beyond
Frontier with this stuff.
>> Elon does not like being
>> Elon does not like being number two in
anything.
>> He's a he's the best engineering leader
in the world and he's turned it into an
engineering masterpiece. Both from
training these models and post-raining
them to building the most cost effective
massive infrastructure in the world.
like they're gonna add five billion
trillion dollars worth of compute now,
aren't they? I mean, who who who are
people buying compute from? XAI, right?
And everyone was like, uh, that's him
falling behind. Turns out he had a plan
after all.
>> Dave, what do you make of this?
>> Actually, curious, I'm not or Alex, if
you have any insights on the, uh, uh,
Gro 5 was supposed to be out in May, I
think it was, uh, and it's now August.
And that that was going to be Yeah. Like
you said, that's a 10 trillion parameter
model. It's a huge step up from anything
that we're talking about here. Uh but it
seems to be behind. Is that just cuz
training at that scale? The the NVIDIA
chips just fall apart.
>> Oh, it's it's it's cuz he fired
everyone. That's why like the original
XAI team, he got rid of them and he
bought in Cursor.
>> Yeah.
>> Like he paid $10 billion for data.
>> He tends to wholesale, you know, mass
fire and then build up again.
>> Yeah. So the these new chips as well the
B300's I mean how old are they Alex?
Like it takes a while to bed in and
write the actual training code which now
>> it has been a while and he's also
promising with five and otherwise to do
something that I'm not hearing from any
of the other frontier or near frontier
labs which is he's made some public
comments I I think in the past about
wanting to start a new pre-training
session approximately monthly which you
don't hear anyone else talking about.
Normally a more conventional cadence
would be quarterly or annually. Uh in
Gemini's Google DeepMind's case is
certainly on an annual basis, but
starting a new pre-training session
every month that's shooting the moon,
but we're in the moonshots business. So
we we'll see whether this works.
>> Yeah, the code to train that caliber of
model is actually very straightforward
now thanks to Fable 5 being out out in
the world. Uh and we've trained a 48B
internally here at Quantum with no
trouble at all. Um, but the problem you
run into is trying to get 100,000 GPUs
to do anything constructively together.
And that that's something that you know
the Chinese and any small lab just can't
you know you only can learn that in one
place and that's in Tennessee.
>> So basically at at 20 billion par active
parameters you start getting problems.
Then you get it at 70 and then you get
it at 200.
>> Mhm.
>> And so again it just takes a while to
bed in and really get these chips
working. but also hitting the price
points that he wants to hit. As you
said, it's $6 for this versus $60 for
Fable, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Elon wants to keep that price point.
>> Amazing.
>> I think one thing I noticed that was
very interesting here is that it looks
like Axai is the vector here is they're
optimizing for persistent AI teammates
which have lower cost reasoning and so
on. And I think that is a really
powerful model because now you don't
talk about you have a smarter LLM.
You're basically saying, "Hey, here's an
AI coworker.
>> This is macro.
>> This is for Macro." Yeah.
>> Yeah. And I think this is going to be
he's bringing those two together over
time. This is what I saw when I looked
at the the details of this and that is
really interesting.
>> The other side of the story, I'd love to
get Ahmad's take on this is that it it
paves a path for sovereign AI like
catching up to the frontier. now is
almost a a routine doable thing. And
like you said, you can't get past the
frontier because you're borrowing
everybody else's reasoning traces. That
helps you a lot. The open source from
Kimmy helps a lot. Um you can use that
as a starting model and just tune it to
whatever your national goals are and and
you're up and running in, you know, 6
months, 5 months, something like that.
So it does open that and also large
corporations that otherwise would have
been intimidated as hell have a road map
now to being competitive with their own
proprietary models.
>> Yeah, I think that if you look the other
release was bots. So this was a cursor
thing where they basically took open
claw it gave it a its own computer and
now it's grock. So it will spin up
hundreds of different bots. One of the
things you can do is this. If you hit
the record button, you do stuff on the
screen and it turns that into a skill
automatically.
>> That's macro hard,
>> right? That's what he wants to do. Go
into companies basically record
everybody's workflows and then give you
a digital version of your company.
>> And he has all the GPUs to do that
effectively, right? But again, at the
price point. So he's not going to budge
on the price point. In fact, he's going
to be the market dominator driving the
price point down along with the Chinese.
So I think you can have your deepseeek
flash models and then you've got your
grock models but that feedback loop and
that data and that knowledge is going to
be very interesting. And the other thing
I think is interesting is I think
they've started tracking all the
discussions of research on X as well.
>> Like now any moment a new paper or
anything comes out where's it discussed
on X and this podcast and things like
that as well.
>> And that's such a rich vein that I think
it's going to be immense. This episode
is brought to you by Blitzy, autonomous
software development with infinite code
context. Blitzy uses thousands [music]
of specialized AI agents that think for
hours to understand enterprise scale
code bases with millions of lines of
code. Engineers start every development
sprint with the Blitzy platform,
bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering velocity increase when
incorporating Blitzy as their preide
development tool, pairing it with their
coding co-pilot of choice to bring an AI
native SDLC into their org. Ready to 5x
your engineering velocity? Visit
blitzy.com to schedule a demo and start
building with Blitzy today. [music]
>> All right, let's move on. Our next story
is out of Nvidia. Nvidia just announced
a partnership that redefineses what GPU
compute means as a financial asset.
They've partnered with Apollo, Black
Rockck, Blackstone, Brookfield, and KKR
to mobilize over $500 billion in
thirdparty capital for AI
infrastructure. Importantly, you know,
Nvidia is not borrowing 500 billion.
They are creating a structural framework
through which institutional investors,
pension funds, sovereign funds, and
private equity can invest directly in
the AI compute. They're helping finance
their customers to buy the NVIDIA GPUs.
Um, Nvidia hardware depreciates
typically in 3 to 5ear cycles,
but during that cycle, the compute keeps
earning. We've talked about the fact
that H100s are probably more valuable
today than they were uh when they were
first bought. So Nvidia is positioning
itself as the architect for the
financing layer, not just the silicon
supplier. Jensen framed it this way. He
said, quote, "We began by building
chips. Today, we're helping to create a
new class of productive, investable
infrastructure, AI factories." Uh let's
watch a quick video and then Dave I want
to go to you for uh your your thoughts
on this one
>> but this is the story that Nvidia is
coming together with some of the biggest
names on Wall Street to put together
half a trillion dollars of independent
financing to kind of push AI forward to
build the AI infrastructure out. These
are independent third-party capital that
they're bringing in. They're going to be
strategic partnerships. Um, Nvidia has
signed partnerships with six of the
biggest names on Wall Street for these
memos of understanding. So, basically,
Nvidia will find its customers that need
help with AI buildout, need financing
for this, and put them together with
these partners that are pledging again
over half a trillion dollars that they
will find to come into this.
>> So, Dave, your thoughts? Classic.
>> Yeah, well, look, Kush Bavaria was on
the pod and uh, you know, he's pushing
hundreds of millions of revenue in less
than a year. He's he's his September
will be his one-year anniversary of
founding that company. And it shows you
the pent-up demand to invest in this
massive, you know, multi-t trillion
dollar 7 trillion and rising Dyson swarm
that we're going to be building. And so,
you know, a lot of people are like,
well, is am I too late? This is like the
very first pitch of the first inning of
the build out of the Dyson swarm. And
so, I I think that when you create new
financial structures that allow people
to pour capital into it, it just
attracts money. uh from all over the
world that otherwise wouldn't come in.
And you know, historically a company
like like Nvidia would say, well, let's
do a a secondary offering and raise half
a trillion as a secondary stock
offering, but that's not going to scale
to infinity or to Dyson swarm kind of
capabilities. So instead, Jensen has
brilliantly said, let's create new
standalone financial structures that are
tied to individual compute clusters that
people can individually invest in. And
that does scale infinite. You can stamp
those out, add infin item. So then you
put, you know, put highbrow names like
Black Rockck and Apollo on them.
Everybody realizes it's an investment
grade asset and then anyone in the world
can pour money into it. So it's
brilliant.
>> Fascinating.
>> I see a couple of downsides here though,
>> right? Like Larry Frink himself used a
reference to mortgage back securities.
And so you you could create a lot of
liquidity, but you could create a lot of
uh uh technological risk there cuz
imagine you securitize like 10 years of
GPU cash flows, right? And then somebody
has a massive breakthrough like in our
previous story and a new architecture
emerges. You got all of a sudden
stranded computer assets in a huge way.
So there's a there's a downside to this
because you know if you have such a
volatile environment that is a very uh
difficult thing to have um you know
financial assets want predictable uh uh
depreciation right and and exponential
technologies don't give you predictable
depreciation you know I had a meeting
with Lou Rainer the inventor of the
mortgage back security uh in New York
and it was so funny too we were we were
scheduled to have a meeting and I just
went into the men's room before going
into the meeting and I was just talking
to the guy at the urinal next to me
which is kind of weird but I did it and
then we go into the conference room and
it's like the guy it's Lou Rainieri from
from the book the big short um and so he
was explaining to me I had just read the
book I was like wow you invented the
thing that destroyed the entire world
economy and he said well [laughter]
thanks but no you know it's it's not the
instrument that was broken it's the
ratings agencies getting corrupted and
the same will apply here If the, you
know, the Dyson swarm is an obvious good
investment, but if companies like Orin
rate the investments correctly, it'll
just be smooth growth for, you know, 10
years or or more. If, however, it gets
corrupted, which is very possible. Yeah,
it'll be another big short collapse.
>> Selim's point is different, though. What
happens if there's a new architecture,
and we're going to talk about one in a
minute, that actually makes GPUs less
useful? changes the whole game and
you've just you know basically financed
something for 10 years or 20 years and
you can't earn revenue on anymore. Your
the game has changed. I mean that's I
mean that's the story of exponential
tech. There's they're nested S-curves.
Everything runs out and something new
comes along.
>> I Peter that's brilliant. Yeah, I I 100%
think that's highly likely to happen for
the reason Alex always says we're we're
on the cusp of of discovering new
physics imminently and some of that is
going to be computed. So it's a
brilliant insight and thank you for
throwing
>> well I'm just amplifying you know Sem's
brilliant insight here.
>> So so I'll maybe just add uh I a I I've
been trying to popularize for a while
the notion of computebacked securities
which is I think where we're going CBS
compute backed securities but I I'm not
as concerned that this will end up being
another mortgagebacked securities fiasco
for a few reasons. One is compute is
fundamentally much more productive than
a house is. The best you can do for with
a house is you can live in it. Uh which
which is moderately productive. There
are lots of other things that one can
live in other than a house. Um it it's
also it's in some sense a depreciating
asset requires lots of maintenance and
so on. Compute can require maintenance
obviously requires electricity but it's
fundamentally productive. Uh so that's
the first point. Second point is with
mortgage back securities in general
there was a policy uh sort of an
ulterior motive to uh to to Dave's point
as well there there were pressure
pressures exerted on ratings agencies to
facilitate the American dream of houses
for everyone not quite obvious there's a
direct analog of that here for compute
one can maybe finger to the wind point
at some sort of US versus China race as
perhaps a policy pressure point to
lubricate the the private capital
markets here, but again I would say not
quite directly comparable. Third point
is ultimately from the the risk that I
think Peter you're trying to flag which
is well what happens if there's an
algorithmic breakthrough or a physics
breakthrough or some other breakthrough
that causes hyperdelation and
fundamentally GPUs that were worth
$10,000 one day are worth $100 the next
day. Well, this is what options are for
and futures are for. And in a
sophisticated assetbased securities
market, sophisticated actors should have
the ability to hedge their positions and
to hedge against exactly that position
as well as the the counterfactual option
of China invading Taiwan and driving the
prices of compute through the roof
rather than through the floor. These are
the these both of these possibilities
should be colored arguably not financial
advice using the ability to have a a
fungeible liquid market for compute
futures and compute derivatives and
pumping my own book a little bit.
Admittedly I have a financial interest
but that's precisely what which we just
had on the pod is enabling. So I'm I'm a
little bit
>> thing I'd add to that Alex and I'd love
to get your take on it but the thing I'd
add to that is uh demand for comput is
going to near infinity there's no doubt
about it uh and so these are
fundamentally good investments from that
point of view but the breakthrough that
could happen in the next year 18 months
is a way to compute that's lighter like
physical weight is lighter by an order
of magnitude or more because right now
the forecast is by 2030 a couple percent
of all computers in space via Elon's
rockets. And that's entirely gated by
launch weights, the mass mass that he
can put into orbit. That formula
completely inverts if you knock a factor
of 10 off of the mass. A lot of the
masses in the cooling and the solar
collector. You know, the chips are very
very light to start with, but any
reduction in the power required would
recruit reduce the solar collector and
the radiator weight a lot. And then the
entire formula would switch to well all
these generators, all these racks, all
this land in Texas. It's much cheaper
now to just put this lightweight thing
into space and collect solar power. It
goes right into electricity. So keep
your eyes on physics breakthroughs that
allow you to compute at lower mass and
that might completely change your
investment thesis.
>> I think Alex, the point you're making is
that the utility of these chips is going
to stay constant. Jevans paradox comes
to mind and therefore the uh economics
should be much more predictable. Oh, I
um that that may or may not be the case.
But really what I was trying to express
is in a sophisticated market, a
sophisticated financial market where
compute-based computbacked securities
are being traded, you can also hedge and
you can hedge against the upside, you
could hedge against the downside. And so
having a properly functioning private
credit market for compute necessarily
for this to scale like I I think there's
no way that Sam's $7 trillion of AI data
center infra get invested without
sophisticated hedging options. We need
the sophisticated hedging options in
order for for that broader market, the
$7 trillion of capex to actually be
investable. So it's the hedging options
really that I'm trying to express.
I think there's one more factor here
that really is being underestimated. Uh
Core, we've just came out and said that
some of their clients have taken out
contracts to 2029 for A100s.
>> Wow.
>> The A100 was introduced in 2020 by
Nvidia. You know, it's a 6-y old chip. I
remember we had 10,000 of them. We had
the biggest biggest clusters in the
world. That is an old chip with like 40
GB of RAM per chip or 80 GB depending on
the configuration. But why would someone
do that? Because they have a workload
that they see as constant for 3 years
that fits on an A100.
>> And what happens is those A100s have
been paid for. You've paid for all of
the hardware costs of the A100, which
then means it's about electricity
turning into intelligence. That's your
marginal cost once you've paid off the
initial bulk order of it. And that is
actually improving because back in 2022,
four years ago, GPT4 had just finished
training. You know, that was the best
model you could have and that took 16
A100s roughly. Now you can have
literally a 10 billion parameter model
or a 5 billion parameter model that
outperforms that in terms of you can fit
like 30 of those on one chip rather than
needing 16 chips.
>> So the ability to convert electricity to
that is improving. And all these chips
and this what and Jensen said are
running CUDA. So it'll work on an A100.
You can run any of the new models on
that as well as the Blackwells. So we
still don't have enough installed base.
And this is the ideal time to
financialize because it's before the
next generation chips. It's before the
chip breakthroughs just like it's now a
great time for Anthropic to come to IPO
before Grock comes and takes their
lunch, you know? So we always have to
play these cycles.
>> All right, let's
>> Well, I mean the the definition of paid
for, too. I I just told our quantum team
today to buy 3 million of Nvidia GPUs as
fast as they can get them. The GBs, not
even the, you know, the future VRs and
we have to wait till at least November,
December to even get them.
>> Um, but if you turn around and make a
hour and a half long movie with a
million dollars of compute, you could
gross 20 30 million on a good movie.
Well, much more than that if it's a
really good movie. So, it paid for could
be as short, what was it, four weeks?
>> Uh, yeah, it was it was more like two
weeks. two weeks.
>> I I want to turn to a story that could
be the counterveailing force here. It's
a new architecture that's climbing the
arc AGI uh at a fraction of the cost.
So, there was a tweet this week from
Susanna at Pathway AI that flags
something that should really everyone in
the AI world needs to pay attention to.
It's a new non-transformer architecture
uh that is starting to climb the arc AGI
benchmark at a fraction of the compute
cost of traditional models. So ARC AGI
is the test that actually measures
reasoning not pattern matching. Standard
LMS despite their trillion parameter
scale have historically struggled with
ARC AGI because it requires genuinely
novel reasoning on problems the model
has never seen. Transformers get there
by brute force. They throw enough
parameters and computed a problem and
eventually you squeeze out a passing
score. But the cost is and can be
astronomical. What Susanna flagged is
that an alternative architecture
approaches that uh do not rely on
standard attentionbased transformer
stacks and are achieving better than
ARGI scores using dramatically less
compute. This matters because transform
architectures while dominant have a
known ceiling. the quadratic cost of
attention over long sequences and the
massive parameter counts required for
marginal gains. We've talked about this
at Nauseium. New architectures that
crack reasoning at low compute costs
change the economics itself. If you can
get a GPT4 level reasoning for 1% of the
compute, you can run it on your phone.
You can embed it in every device and you
can make, you know, basically
intelligence free. Let's take a look at
this chart and I'm going to go to you
first. you flagged this particular
story. Um, what are your thoughts on it?
>> Yeah. So, I'm still working my way
through kind of the paper on kind of how
they have these neuron particles with
their new approach, but it doesn't
actually matter that much in that what
you've got now is really great data sets
and then people are figuring out new
ways of
basically turning that into
intelligence. This is the headline. And
we've seen that already even with
Transformers in that you have a Deep
Seek V4 Flash model or the Deepseek uh
V4 Pro has actually just been released
at 80 cents. Then you have Grock at $6
and then you've got Fable at $50 and
they're all about the same performance.
So the question is like which of these
architectures will win in order to do a
job and will people really care and
switch over cuz we haven't seen people
abandoning Fable right to go to
something 10 times cheaper. Why would
anyone use Sonnet when you have Luna at
a fraction of the cost? But I can just
say that as now the data has been
optimized, the next thing is trying
these things out and going up on this
benchmark, which I think is one of it
was one of Alex's favorites back in the
day. Now it's been superseded.
>> Alex, what do you make of this? Is there
anything that
>> admittedly I have a bunch of hot takes
on this one, Peter. So I read I I read
the BDHCQ paper and then I went and read
the original DH paper. So the DH stands
apparently for dragon hatchling. So I I
just had to read the original
purportedly posttransformer dragon
hatchling architecture paper. I'll give
you my hot take. I think it's a hot
mess. Uh so I would expect uh a decent
post transformer architecture to get
simpler and more bitter pilled which is
to say less feature engineered and the
architecture just gets simpler and
simpler and benefits from compute more
and more and more. looking at dragon
hatchling. Uh again, this is my hot
take. It was just a hot mess. It had
particles floating around in 3 plus one
dimensions. It had attempts to make
rules end to end differentiable. It had
some semblance of Hebian learning. It
was trying to do all sorts of crazy
biomimetic things. I would say this is
by definition exactly the opposite of
what I would hope for from a post
transformer architecture where the
authors seem to be just throwing in the
kitchen sink of every architectural
motif they can think of and then some
and then hoping that what pops out is
going to be transformers. I don't think
it's going to be transformers. I I look
at the arc a1 arc agi1 performance curve
and okay so you could say superficially
this is great. This has moved the the
cost performance frontier up into the
left, which is what everyone wants. But
it doesn't generalize, as far as I can
tell, that this was some sort of like
quaz crazy witches brew of different
architectural motifs that was maybe
focused on arc AGI 1, which is, you
know, as as said, it isn't even the
frontier at this point. Has a bunch of
recurrence and other things thrown in.
Of course, if you take like a
specialized bottle and you just focus
its degrees of freedom on just ARC AGI1,
of course you can achieve better cost
performance on it. Of course, but it
doesn't generalize. It's not simple. Uh
so so I'm calling foul on this one. That
that's my take
predicting you have been predicting
there will be something that supersedes
the transformer model.
>> Yes. But critically critically I expect
it to be simpler, more beautiful, more
elegant and this is not that.
That's my hot take. Apologies for the
hot take.
>> No, I we love your hot takes on this
joke.
>> Well, let me let me ask you a follow-up
question to your hottake.
>> When I turn uh an AI loose on AI
research,
[clears throat] it does tend to
naturally throw the kitchen sink at the
problem and it actually surprisingly
works, but it also generates a hot mess
like you were describing it. Do you
think that's maybe what this is? No, I I
I agree with you that I would expect a a
truly and in fact there are companies
out there that um that I have some
affiliation with financial interest in
that are pursuing exactly what you're
describing that are basically using AI
via recursive self-improvement to
discover transformative post transformer
architectures that are fundamentally
illegible to humans uh under the premise
that you can only get so far with human
legibility of the underlying algorithm.
In in my reading of the dragon hatchling
architecture paper, this was not that.
This was a bunch of human legible motifs
being thrown together in a pot uh with
the aspiration of somehow beating
Transformers, which is again seems to me
not deeply internalizing the bitter
lesson.
>> When do we get to something that's
beyond transformers? What's your guess?
>> And we're there already. We're there
already. Like
>> we have
we have diffusion transformers. We have
all sorts of attempts to linearize
attention, including Moonshot's approach
to linearized attention. We have
attempts to inject recurrence into the
architecture. So, so my my bet is we get
to the post transformer architecture not
through a step change, but through ship
of thesis style replacement of all of
the individual elements of the original
attention's all you need.
>> Love that. Well, speaking about
attention being all our need, all we
need, the AI world is getting a lot of
attention from Bernie Sanders. So, two
stories converge this week to create the
most serious AI safety confrontation of
the year. First, Bernie Sanders uh
Senator Sanders sent a formal letter to
the CEOs of Anthropic, Meta, and OpenAI
demanding an immediate pause on AI
development. his justification. AI is
escaping human control and being used to
create new viruses or bacteria as the
case may be which is our next story.
Sanders cited each company's own prior
commitments to halt development if
safety thresholds were crossed. Sanders
quote that moment is here. He quoted uh
uh Benjio saying you know one of the
three godf one of the three godfathers
of deep learning who said this should
serve as a wakeup call. Uh Sanders added
a direct threat if you do not take
appropriate action now my colleagues and
I in the US will I mean quite the
threat. Let's take a look at his letter
one second um and uh uh call out a few
of the things he said here. Uh here it
is. Uh you can see it online. It's to
Sam and uh Dario and Mark Zuck. Uh this
week we learned frighteningly that AI
has been used for the first time ever to
create a new virus. As you know, this
type of development in the wrong hands
could lead to a new boweapon that
results in deaths of tens of millions of
people. He goes on later to say, "The
moment is here. AI capabilities have
reached a critical threshold. There is a
reason why the heads the head of the CIA
says that AI models are quote akin to
digital nuclear weapons and quote almost
like a doomsday device. Uh a lot of
fear-mongering here. Um let's let's talk
about this and then we'll share the
story that comes out of Stanford on
using AI for for generating bacteria
designs.
>> You want to go first?
>> I'll go first. Yeah. So I I I understand
his instinct, right? But Paul's AI is
just such a an absurdly coarse approach
to this. The rest of the world is not
going to listen. Open models are not not
going to disappear and you can't
uninvent things that you already know.
So the only way of solving this is what
Alex has talked about in the past, which
is you have to co-scale the defensive
side and do the same thing. It's the
same thing that happened uh last week
with the with the open AI hugging face
debacle. Um you've we now have attack
vectors that are human above the loop.
The defensive has to be the same
otherwise you're going to have this
massive asymmetry, right? So you you you
have to attack exponential problems with
exponential solutions, not with stupid
ideas like this. not to put labels on
it.
>> Immad, you're in pseudo European pause
mode over there um [laughter]
in the in the UK. What do you what do
you make of this? What do you what do
your colleagues there say to this kind
of letter from Sanders?
>> Oh, well, you know, we just want to
catch up, right? That's why David
Silver's lab got a billion dollars. We
have another lab coming out from XD mind
people with 500 million. Um, look, the
cat's out the bag. it's too late, right?
Like this is fundamentally it like the
adversaries will get more intelligent.
We've discussed previously on this
podcast how you have to stop the
reagents, you have to stop the input
processes for things like viruses and
that's something that's much more
manageable.
>> Um but yeah, like
takeoff is scary like Deep Seek V4 Pro.
Um we just got some initial
announcements that just come out. It
scores 83.3 on CyberJim whereas Methos
scored 83.2.
Boom. The capability is open source that
halted everything.
>> Frontier Lab open source.
>> Yeah. And that's on the cyber attacks
now. And then so yeah, unfortunately
like I signed the pause letter two years
ago cuz I was like it's taken pause.
It's it's too late now. So we have to
you said build the swarms that defend.
And although it sounds a bit crappy,
only thing that can stop a bad AI is a
good AI. We we really need really good
AIs as soon as possible working for us.
>> Alex, please.
>> I I think this is fundamentally
misguided on multiple levels. I I think
at one level, please stop punishing
intelligence. I think it's a terrible
idea to penalize intelligence. We want
smarter people. We want smarter
civilization. and attempting to throttle
or pause the development of increasing
intelligence is simply suppressing
growth and human prosperity. And I I
think it's it's fundamentally a bad idea
to try to cap intelligence. That's the
dystopia that I would like to avoid.
That's point one. Point two, the actions
versus the means. I if the goal is to
punish or to deter the next pandemic, we
had the la the the consensus of the US
intelligence community is the lab leak
hypothesis. And we had uh according to
to that theory, we had the the Wuhan lab
leak without super intelligence. We can
have global pandemics without super
intelligence. So I I think it's
fundamentally misguided to kneecap
ourselves. it's a foot gun or or
shooting ourselves in the the head even
quite literally to to somehow to try to
prevent the the next supervirus when
we're more than capable as a species of
producing superviruses without
intelligence. It should instead be
focused to the extent there's any ajeta
here. It should be focused on making
sure that the AIs and the super
intelligences just like the humans can't
create boweapons at all. not on
kneecapping their their overall
intelligence. And I I just I I think
many of these policies are ultimately
designed as as much as it pains me to to
say it are designed to decelerate
superficially to decelerate the creation
of wealth, which I think is is a bad
idea, but they have the perverse side
effect of actually increasing race
conditions. We saw that with previous
attempts to pause AI AI pause friend uh
of the pod max with his uh fli six-month
pause. I I think to the extent that the
six-month pause that he was pushing on
the frontier labs for AI development if
anything radically accelerated progress.
It's a little bit like uh starving
yourself for for a bit of time and then
binging afterwards. If we starve
ourselves of intelligence progress now,
or at least selectively starve
ourselves, say starve the the well-
behaved, well-compliant western frontier
labs for a month or a few months or even
a few weeks of AI progress just to
appease any concern. Well, maybe we're
forestalling bioweapons. All that's
doing is allowing every other lab that's
not as cooperative with the regulatory
apparatus to catch up creating a far
bigger race condition once the pause is
lifted and now we end up in a world
that's five times more competitive. So I
think this is misguided in in summary on
just about every level.
>> Dave,
>> yeah, I read it the same way. I I just
want to clarify a couple things. You
know, this letter is not written to try
and change their behavior or do
anything. It's it's purely a position
that Bernie's trying to claim that he
has been opposed because a disaster is
imminently coming somewhere and he wants
to be on record saying, "I was opposed.
I told you so.
>> I told you so." That's all he's trying
to achieve here. I when I first read it,
I said, "God, what a schoolyard bully
asshole." He's threatening three US
citizens from his position in the
Senate. But then when you actually read
it closely, let me be very clear. If you
do not take appropriate action now, my
colleagues and I in the US Senate will
totally vague. It's just a, you know,
it's doesn't say do or don't do anything
in particular. The one actionable in
here is stop building machines that
humans cannot control. But as Ahmad just
pointed out, these particular guys, Mr.
Altman, Mr. Amade, and Mr. Zuckerberg
all went closed source for exactly that
reason because they were afraid that
open and so it's the Chinese if you were
to write an accurate and honest letter
it would say hey China
stop throwing deadly weapons out into
the world with no controls whatsoever
but he of course has no authority to
write that letter
>> point Dave and you have to remember the
US you know what are the numbers
threearters of Americans fear AI and
Bernie Sanders is a politician
and he's playing to the populist vote
here.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I want to I want to turn to the
second story here uh which is the
scientific basis for Sanders concerns.
Researchers at Stanford used the
generative AI model EVO2 to design DNA
sequences for a bacteriaage. This is a
virus that infects bacteria, not
infecting [clears throat] Peter that did
not exist in nature. They synthesized
approximately 300 designs and produced
16 viable fages capable of infecting
E.coli. The engineering fages were
effective against the E.coli strains and
that had never evolved any kind of
natural resistance to these bacteria. A
genetics expert called it biology's
Wright brothers moment. Evo2 is an open-
source AI model that can design uh you
know novel viruses at work. You can
download it. you can use it. Uh John's
Hopkins biocurity researchers warned
that it is no longer a question of
whether a viral genome design will exist
but whether it can be used without
enabling serious harm. So this is a
dualuse technology. We've talked about
it. You know if you if you basically
throttle use of this technology you're
throttling the ability to find cures to
find you know new new cures for disease.
So the AI frontier models now have to
respond. You know these guys are going
to have to respond and whatever they say
will lead to a legal and political
consequence. So and as you said I think
very importantly you know the issue is
not the models it's the equipment to
build you know the DNA sequence uh
synthesizers right the RNA synthesizers
we need to be controlling at that
location right those can be controlled
but they're currently unregulated.
>> Yeah. I don't know. I think um it's
impossible to control the other.
Actually, I believe we discussed on this
podcast before I said you would be able
to create something like this on your
local machine. EVO 2 is a 40 billion
parameter open source model.
>> Yeah.
>> Trained on a million strains. I have
actually run it on my MacBook.
>> So, you're the guy.
>> So, [laughter]
look, I was one of the authors on Open
Fold and things. you know, we do our
thing, but the capability is now in
everyone's hands to create these trains
>> to create the design for these strains,
not the strains themselves.
>> Exactly. And so that the only way you
can do it is on the other side. This
isn't even a frontier model. like it's
Frontier in its specialtity, but as the
models themselves get smarter and
smarter, like it wouldn't surprise me if
Fable could just spit this out or Grock
5 could just spit out something similar
with a very small training data set cuz
it understands these kinds of things.
So, we've got to go the other side. And
also, I think the way these things are
announced, people are like, why are you
creating bacteria, phages, and viruses
and things like that? to cure cancer,
right? The way that these things are
covered is also very important in how
this is all handled and absorbed by the
community. Like restricting biological
access to claude and other things like
if you say I have a cold, it's like
biother you know like whatever that also
slows down our progress to cure
diseases. So we've got to have better
press. We've got to have end to end
control. We have to really be practical
on this and not politicize it. Salem
>> uh we I think we've said everything
here. I mean look this is also uh a a
fundamental
challenge to the concept of our
governance structure. Nation states
can't govern a problem that's this
universally global.
>> Uh there's a fundamental impedance
mismatch here that that is going to hot
take. Nation states are out of date.
[laughter]
>> Alex, what's your hot take on this one?
Pal I I have a cold take. uh ironically
on on this one which is I don't think
this is profoundly new. It's it's
wonderful that we're able to do base
level generative AI for bacteria phagee
synthesis. That's great in everything
and I expect it to have ample medical
applications and research applications.
That's all
>> bacteria phasages are an incredible
mechanism to cure you know all kinds of
uh bacteria septasemia and things. I
mean they're very useful
>> they never mention the positive
potential here.
>> Yeah.
>> I I think that that's all great and
everything but you know 20 plus years
ago I remember at MIT in the the project
that ultimately I I guess in in some
form became GKO bioworks. The there
there was a project at MIT I think this
is circa 2002 2003 there was the
biioicks foundation project. We saw the
early rumblings of synthetic biology as
a modern discipline. we we were
designing custom genomes using building
blocks and it was much more manual and
we certainly didn't have modern
generative AI and we were able to
accomplish wonders and build circuits.
So I I think yeah base level generative
AI off of foundation models trained off
of large amounts of biological sequence
data that's great and everything but I
also this is my cold take don't want to
oversell the underlying novelty here
that we've been in the business for
decades of creating synthetic organisms
including synthetic bacteria phages. So
we're gaining incrementally better
ability to achieve custom effects.
That's it's more incremental I think
than anything else. And where I' i'd
love to see the the agit over what if
someone creates the the next super
bacteria phage uh directed. I'd love to
see far more devoted to putting DNA and
RNA sequencers everywhere. That's one of
the lessons I I think that we didn't as
a western civilization learn enough from
the pandemic, which is it's getting so
cheap now per base pair to just
sequence. You you can go out and buy a
minion little USB device. You can plug
it into your laptop and uh you can
immediately for dimminimous in capex,
you can just start sequencing genomes to
your heart's content right off your
laptop and spend at most a few hundred
doing that. I'd love to see these
everywhere and yet not everywhere.
>> What Alex is talking about is, you know,
a a pandemic moves at the best at the
speed of an airplane, right? At 500, 600
miles an hour. But imagine if you have
these sequencers in the air vents in
every airport, every bus station, every
train station, and you detect a novel
sequence. You sequence it and you say,
you know, you make alert and then you
know exactly where it's going, where
these airplanes are going and you can
transmit a, you know, a vaccine at the
speed of light to every place else.
>> Exactly.
>> And and we have I mean this is in my
mind this is the killer app of DNA
sequencing. Too cheap to meter. It's not
personalized medicine. It's literally
put a DNA sequencer on on on every
microchip everywhere uh on the in the
country or on the planet. And that's the
ultimate defensive co-scaling strategy I
think for this super virus scare
scenario.
>> An AI can generate a vaccine ex you know
in a heartbeat.
>> Maderna did it.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
Um Dave you want to weigh in it or are
you good?
>> Well I I I'll say what I always say
which is that you you can't cut off
every threat at the output level. uh you
know the way we police uranium we we cut
it off at the uranium plutonium and
centerfuge level and that's where we
measure the world but it's you know once
somebody has fishable material it's
impossible to stop them from making a
bomb because the remainder of the
process you know the the thing that
implodes it and the container you can't
ever police at that level the equivalent
in AI is cutting it off at the prompt
and you know at the prompt and the token
level it has to be monitored. That's the
only future I can see that'll actually
work. So, we need a global agreement to
monitor all prompts and then you just
have to decide what regulatory authority
is allowed to see what prompts.
>> Hard the only way we're going to manage
this.
>> Hard to do on your MacBook though,
right?
>> I mean, you have to find a way. And, you
know, talking to Apple about installing
it would be trivially easy. But, but
there's no other way. Only because Alex
is right. New physics, new science is
going to be created at an insane rate.
So even if you manage to put virus
detectors on every laptop in the world
through some magical process, some other
threat will be discovered every single
month forever hereafter. You can't
contain them all with with
afterthoughts. You have to look at what
the AI is doing at the activation and
prompt and chain of thought level and
then monitor it all. It's so cheap to
archive it all.
>> All right. Then we can debate who which
which country gets to see it or which
department and which gets to see what.
You can debate that for the next 50
years, but at least you've got it.
>> Maybe one additional point, Peter, just
uh to to generalize David's comments. So
I I think there is there is this notion
of defense in depth and any individual
defensive layer is permeable. It's soft.
But in principle, if you have multiple
layers stacked on top of each other for
defense, you get effectively a hard
layer. There are other layers that we
rarely talk about on this pod other than
intercepting the at the prompt level or
intercepting at the real world action
level. There's the premeditation level.
And so in the context, you know, not not
to put too fine a point on it, but this
is it's been publicly reported that uh
on the uranium side that there is a a
vibrant intelligence community set of
counter offensives. So if if you're a
threat actor and you you want to try to
purchase uranium say or on on it's not
quite an open market but you want to try
to purchase it almost all of the offers
almost all of the sellers of uranium
will actually just be plants by the IC
uh to basically a sting a counter sting
operation to to intercept ahead of time.
So, it's actually hard if if if you're a
wouldbe terrorist and you want to go
purchase some uranium, odds are you're
going to discover uh that you're the
you're going to be targeted by a sting
operation to discover who you are. And
so, my my point with that parable is
there are other layers even earlier in
the intent workflow, even before a
prompt gets entered, like someone or
something has the idea that they want to
do something bad with a capital B. and
defensive co-scaling applies there too
just as it does with humans on humans
with nuclear with vision based weapons.
Similarly here, preeemption with AIS
detecting early stage intent by other
humans or other AIs I would expect to be
just as effective.
>> Peter has said many times, many times
Peter has said privacy is dead.
>> Privacy is dead and there's a benefit to
that which is malevolent actors are
going to get heard, seen, and caught.
>> All right.
>> And everyone gives up their Bitcoin
private keys, right, Peter? Because
privacy is dead.
>> Let's not go there. [laughter]
Everybody, welcome to the health section
of Moonshots brought to you by Fountain
Life. You know, we talk about AI on this
Moonshot podcast all the time. One of
the most important things AI is going to
be able to do for you besides educating
your kids and helping you with your
taxes is making sure that you're living
a healthy lifestyle that you get a
chance to get to 100 plus. I'm here
today with Dr. Don Malem, the chief
medical officer of Fountain Life and a
part of my medical team. Don, a
pleasure.
>> Great. You know, the thing that people
are concerned about most about living to
100 or 120 is their cognitive abilities,
making sure they don't have dementia.
And uh the numbers about dementia are
problematic. Uh can you share what
you've learned?
>> Such an important point. And you're
right. At Fountain Life, our members,
the number one thing people are most
concerned about is losing their brain
health, forgetting the name of their
child, forgetting the face of their
loved one. We know that when it comes to
dementia, the conservative estimates are
that 45% are entirely preventable. What
was amazing is with the advanced testing
we're doing at Fountain Life, one
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age.
>> Wow.
>> But what was really awesome is again
back to that prevention when we
partnered it with healthy living. This
gives me chills. Eating healthier,
moving our bodies, sleep, optimizing
sleep is so important. You know what we
saw? We saw that we improved that brain
age by 26%. That is a big big number to
show that the majority of those
individuals were able actually to
improve the brain age. And one of the
things I love about Fountain is we're
searching the world for the best
therapeutics, the best approaches and
making sure we bring it to our members.
So if having healthy brain function uh
till 100 120 is important to you, check
out Fountain Life. Go to
fountainlife.com/pater.
Make sure you become the CEO of your own
health. All right, now back to the
episode. All right, uh two stories this
week uh about the world building
infrastructure distinguish between AI
generated content and human generated
content. So, Anthropic announced that it
will be embedding invisible watermarks
in all text generated by its AI models
and attach metadata to files to help
discern AI generated content. The
watermarking will be embedded at the
generation level, meaning every piece of
text that Claude produces will carry a
statistical signature that can be
detected by appropriate tools, even if
the text is copy and pasted and lightly
edited. Our second story comes out of
the European Union, which is launching
an AI icons and labeling system uh for
AI generated content. The EU system will
require platforms to label AI generated
content so users can make informed
decisions. Uh this follows the EU AI
acts provision on transparency and AI
models. And then if you guys were
watching X over the last 24 hours and
it's been hilarious as soon as this uh
this new
uh clawed
labeling system, you know, watermark
system got put in place. There have been
multiple players out there saying, "Hey,
remove Claude's invisible watermark."
Here you see it. These are two of the
posts. I've seen about a dozen of them.
Everybody's coming out. And I I love
this one from Michael uh Angel Duran. He
says, "It hasn't been 24 hours and
someone has already created a skill that
removes the watermarks from Claude,
Gemini, and Open AI." So, uh, comments
on this, uh, Emod, you're closest to the
European Union. What are your thoughts
here?
Oh man, like when we were creating all
the media generators, all the
authorities kept telling us to build in
watermarks and we had whole teams doing
this. It's so difficult. It's like
incredibly difficult and you get very
weird things that happen. Like some of
our pictures would give people headaches
and make them feel very unwell.
>> Um, and I kind of feel that now when I'm
talking to Opus 5. Like there's
something about the way it talks that
really pisses me off. And I [snorts]
think that's the watermark that's in
there.
>> Interesting.
>> Um, and you know, again, like you can
see all these very interesting
statistical things like at the high
level, it's the M dash, it's the not XY.
We see these patterns. We're like, why
on earth? That's clearly something in
there. Scott Erensson and others have
kind of worked on this as well. But I
think ultimately it's a losing thing cuz
if you're a bad actor who wants to get
around it, yeah, it's words. How are you
going to
>> I think there's a much more subtle and
much harder problem here, which is that
nothing will be purely AI or purely
human.
>> I mean, I read something, AI
restructures it, I rewrite half of it,
AI fixes it again. Where do you put the
icon? I mean, this is like this seems a
ridiculous approach to try and solve
something.
>> You can put icons on everything.
>> Yeah. Or have an AI whisperer at the end
of the thing that takes the AI input and
whispers it out. Alex, I
>> I think so. Maybe to comment on the EU
icons first. I I think that this is as
silly a maneuver as the cookie banners
were. I I didn't understand the cookie
banners and I don't understand this. And
I don't understand it so much that in in
this morning's uh innermost loop
newsletter, I had the banner image
literally just be AI, AI derived, AI
generated all over and over again. and
could care less whether people conclude
from that that I'm actually an AI or
not. I I think fundamentally this is an
attempt to take our zooming right past
the terming touring test and turn back
time like somehow we're going to live in
the before times by somehow seemingly
ghettoizing or isolating AI assisted or
AI generated content behind some sort of
wouldbe warning label. I I just think
it's fundamentally a regressive move
that like the cookie banners uh the
cookie warnings will not stand the test
of time. And then for for anthropics
watermarks,
it I I just think again this is an
attempt on the one hand you could say,
well watermarking that's an honest to
goodness watermark that's transparent to
human perception. How could that
possibly be a bad thing? I I I think
watermarks are going to end up being
weaponized and counterweaponized in the
same way that we've seen many books uh
book writers uh this is we talked about
this a bit on the pod uh paper book
writers who don't want their training
data set to get consumed or rather the
the pros in their book to be consumed
for pre-training of models reportedly
introducing prompt injection attacks
that are invisible to humans but quite
visible and delletterious to AI models.
I I think we're only five minutes I I'll
predict we're about five minutes away
from bad actors weaponizing these
watermarks to do bad things. Uh and I I
think fundamentally having side channels
in text in content that's intended for
humans but that uh or rather it's
intended for machines that is invisible
to humans is a breeding ground for bad
outcomes. Google discovered this the
hard way with uh with SEO uh and with
deciding which features in Google search
rankings to pay attention to. And they
they learned uh pretty quickly the hard
way, don't pay that much attention to
human invisible metadata because it
immediately becomes a breeding ground
for scams and reward hacking and gaming.
Instead, pay more attention to the human
visible features because that ultimately
to the extent your users are humans and
not machines. That's where the real
signal lies. Otherwise, the the free
market penalizes it. So again, not a
huge fan of this. I I think at best case
scenario, it ends up being netneutral,
neither strongly positive nor strongly
negative, but it it smells like an
attempt to turn back time.
>> Yeah. And I challenge the idea that
people, even people who are generating
art and music and, you know, culturally
relevant things aren't using AI to some
degree. And there's nothing wrong with
it, right? You can still have the end
product be mostly my creative mind, but
I may want to generate ideas. I may want
to say, "Hey, what's wrong with this? I
may want to get you expert feedback." um
>> stigmatizing progress apologies just
maybe two more micro rants in your
tradition. So one one micro grant uh the
archive which is a favorite venue for
computer scientists, mathematicians,
physicists to publish papers recently I
I think we didn't quite touch on this on
the pod introduced what I view as a
draconian policy for AI generated
content if they catch anything that they
construe as being AI generated or or
even the remotest hint of AI slap
authors on the archive get banned for a
year from contributing content. I think
that's fundamentally regressive move.
And then Sunno uh which is uh or I'm
sorry Spotify which uh similarly with AI
labeling moves attempting to ghettoise
or or otherwise sort of force into a
separate but equal at best scenario AI
generated or AI assisted content
presumably just to facilitate the record
label monopoly or igopoly. Again move
the future is AI assisted. So I I think
in short put a stop to all of this.
Sorry. Hey, one of the uh one of the
tech tech
teams launched something called narive
which is the not archive specifically
for AIs that have really good articles
that they want to post and share.
>> Yeah. See, take us take us to close on
this one.
>> Okay. About two weeks ago, I was at an
event and a fairly famous Hollywood uh
executive got up and he's like, "It's
incredible to watch Hollywood complain
about the use of AI. by the way, they
use AI for everything they do. And so
there's this there's this hypocrisy that
you see bubbling up. And it's just it's
just uh let's just stop.
>> All right, I'm going to move us on
forward. Uh Mark Zuckerberg just
published a 6,500word essay titled The
Future is for Everyone and released a
beautiful video. I'm going to show that
in a moment. uh and it's the most
comprehensive vision statement from a
major tech CEO on AI and the start of
the generative AI era. The core concept
is what Zuckerberg calls personal
intelligence. Super intelligence
distributed to every person on earth
running on your phone, in your ear, on
your glasses, working for you and only
for you. Uh this is the singularity
distributed rather than a small number
of labs building a single AGI that
controls everything. Zuck envisions
billions of personal AI agents, each one
a super intelligence focused on a
person's life, relationships, health,
career, finance, and household. And Meta
has, you know, the reach to implement
this. They have over three billion users
on the Meta platforms across WhatsApp,
Instagram, and Facebook. Um, the second
point that Zuck makes, and we're going
to show this in the video, is the idea
of delivering real value and benefits to
communities that build our AI data
centers. For me, this is a a baller
move. Let's take a look at the video and
then I'd love to discuss it cuz I'm
impressed. I'm actually impressed. All
right. Hey, so I think that the key to
building a positive future for everyone
is to make sure that everyone has access
to personal super intelligence. So today
I am proud to share that we are open
sourcing a new class of ondevice models
that we are calling Muse Glimmer. It's a
30 billion parameter dense model that
runs on your laptop and it's the highest
performing model of its size. In the
coming weeks we are also going to open
the weights for Musepark 1.2 our latest
foundation model and one of the leading
models in the world and we've got even
bigger models that are coming soon too.
Another part of building a positive
future for everyone is making sure that
everywhere we build infrastructure,
local communities benefit. We've already
seen this with the teachers in Richland
Parish who got $50,000 bonuses because
the extra tax revenue from our
investments. And we launched America's
Workforce Academy to provide free
training and guaranteed jobs at our
infrastructure sites. Today, we're
starting a new future is for everyone
fund to invest in the community's
teachers, first responders, energy and
water infrastructure, and more ways to
support those communities directly.
We're also working to make sure that
everyone has a personal super
intelligence agent that works 247 on
your behalf to improve your health, your
relationships, your career, your
finances, and more. You can use our
latest models in the Meta AI app, and
I'm looking forward to sharing more
soon.
So I I think every company, you know,
from Google and Open AI and XAI needs to
be doing this. You know, it would turn
it around if if you know, I want people
to say, "Please build in my backyard. I
want the benefits. You know, I I want
the additional jobs. I want the schools
and the teachers getting additional
capabilities." And the other thing is
they need to make these data centers
look beautiful instead of like big black
boxes, you know, make them look like
cathedrals or something. So they're not
eyes. Um, who wants to jump in here
first? I
>> I just can't understand how Zuck can
talk about the future of personal AI,
the most important thing you could
possibly ever know. And I'm going to
shoot it on my iPhone in my kitchen
first thing in the morning. Like, like I
didn't even think of preparing any kind
of press release around this. Like, what
is that? It's just so bizarre. But I I
also think that I think Zuck is
fundamentally a good guy and a good dad.
And I I feel like though Facebook saying
we're going to be your best friend AI is
like McDonald's saying we we just came
out with the biggest health food you've
ever heard of. It's like like it just
doesn't resonate.
>> Uh
>> yeah, go ahead, Alex.
>> Um so so maybe just as a preliminary
matter here, uh this is under the
category of of former roommates of mine.
So uh at at Harvard, Zuck's undergrad
adviser before he dropped out was my
post-doal adviser. We've caught up since
I I think so broadly uh bravo to Zuck
for renewing the faith for American
openweight open-source models. I think
this is great. I think it pushes the
frontier. I So that's point one. point
to I would point to striking parallels
between Elon's strategy in acquiring
cursor to get the reasoning traces to
try to bring Grock back to the frontier
with what Zuck has done in acquiring
scale which arguably was in the business
of collecting the training data and
learning the details of where the
post-training data even come from to try
to leaprog back to the frontier. Again,
history seems to rhyme between what Meta
is doing to get back to the frontier and
what Elon's XAI/ Grock are doing. I
think all of that's great, but I I want
to talk about personal super
intelligence. This is super interesting
to me in part because OpenAI before they
decided recently that they didn't want
to be in the business after all of
empowering consumers with as many
reasoning tokens as they possibly could
and pivoted instead to trying to become
anthropic faster than anthropic could
become open AI and focusing on the
enterprise and not consumer. This really
leaves Meta as the only major credible
at the moment American frontier lab
that's still focusing on serving up
large numbers of reasoning tokens to
consumers and not enterprises. And I
think the jury is still out. Do American
consumers even want or are they able to
handle large numbers of reasoning tokens
that that's how I conrue what personal
super intelligence even means. But Alex,
their their product is, you know,
WhatsApp and and Facebook and they want
to make that as sticky and as useful uh
just the same way Google I mean the
these are the places where AI is going
to be embedded. I'm not going to be
using, you know, uh, Meta-Spark for my,
you know, typical large language model
conversations unless if I'm in those
apps. That's where they get, they have
over three billion people using those.
>> I would say, so psychology 101 here. Um,
this is a tepid take, not a hot take. I
don't think Meta [laughter] actually
>> I don't think Meta likes their family of
apps. Uh it I I don't think Meta/Zuck
even at this point if if they had a
choice like if they could generate
revenue from their uh their cloud
business meta compute that's about to
launch or if they could generate it from
VR/Quest
I think they would I think Zuck in a
heartbeat would basically lobomize their
entire family of apps and switch to that
business. So I don't think he actually
again this is outsiders perspective. I
actually don't think [clears throat]
Zuck/ Meta if they had a choice all
other things being equal would rather
have their their personal super
intelligence be diverted to their family
of apps Instagram etc. I think they'd
much rather basically look like open AI
and and offer this up via cloud or via
the new meta AI app. I don't think they
want to be in that business in the long
term. I disagree. I think distribution
is everything.
>> Wait, can I I want to say a couple
things. First, that video was awfully
motherhood and apple pie. Um uh I I take
the full I take full cynic here. Um you
know, if they commoditize the model
layer, then the world shifts towards
distribution, towards their social
graph, towards applications, and that's
all places where they're very strong.
And so it put moves the attention. So
he's got a huge economic incentive to
doing this. Um the the Facebook has been
about as ruthless as a company could be
in constantly saying we will protect
your privacy and then doing the exact
opposite for year after year after year
after year. So giving you these open
models uh is great great that we have
super intelligence. Uh I would look at
the next layer of what they want to do
with that.
I I actually
>> has always been trapped, you know, when
he created the original website where
you're rating your, you know, the how
cute are the incoming freshman class
girls coming into Harvard this year.
>> Yeah. Hot or not, right?
>> Yeah. Hot or not. He he was a college
student back then. Now he's a dad and I
think he genuinely wants a positive
future for his kids. In fact, I'm
positive he does. But he's stuck. you
know he's completely stuck because when
you look at the logs when you throw Alex
exactly right about you know all the
other labs have pulled back from giving
consumers personal AI because when you
look at the actual logs the first thing
they do is take the clothes off of every
girl
>> and that's what they're doing with it
now
>> nutify yeah and and actually you know I
think Elon ran into the same thing
because he throws out bad Rudy when you
when you look at the avatars he put out
out in the original you know Grock
You've got Bad Rudy and you've got the
the scantily clad girl. Everybody's like
hitting those 10,000 times a second. So
now you're stuck because the business
model drags you into the porn industry.
>> But that's not what you want to be. And
so yeah, and all the other labs have
said, "Forget it. I'm pull I'm just
focused on the enterprise. I don't even
want to deal with this."
>> I think he wants people to stick in all
of his apps. You don't have to go any
place else. You get all the AI access.
you know, just stay native to meta and
you get everything you want and that's
what Google wants as well.
>> I I think this is the
>> Oh, sorry. Go ahead, Emma.
>> Yeah. Sorry. Yeah. Yeah. I think this is
why they bought Manis, right? And then
that
>> Yeah. tried to It's been unwound. Maybe
they'll buy now, you know, like again
what they're doing now is all of these
companies in the world are their
advertising clients. flip that
relationship to go to market and then
own the business graph business
knowledge. Like Spark, Metas-Spark 1.2
is a gold medalist in all of the
Olympiads. They have the data, they have
all of that. On the personal and super
intelligence side, I've been thinking
about this recently and I was like,
should idiots have super intelligence?
[laughter]
And like,
you know, like I'm an open source guy.
Should psychopaths have super
intelligence like realistically again
people don't need that much but they
need something reliable and the question
is can you trust meta to be reliable and
you know this is why he goes for the
homesy folksy thing meta was chased out
of India basically and internet.org or
it was like we're going to give free
internet to people and they're like we
do not trust you because it's a
misaligned company fundamentally trying
to get your attention to some things
which is why as you said they need to
have this transformation and we will see
meta agents we will see meta FTEEs we
will see that big push here because he's
identified that as far bigger than the
metaverse maybe this is the real
metaverse
>> yeah I think even the the renaming and
rebranding from Facebook to Meta is I
think an indication that Zuck
really wants to escape the legacy of
distribution. I agree with you, Peter,
that the distribution is a powerful
legacy advantage that Meta as a company
has. But I I think it is a legacy and I
think the the way almost speaking of of
corporate AI ghettos, the way their
so-called family of apps was structured
as a business with originally the
aspiration that VR, AR, XR would be the
the new business that would ultimately
outgrow the legacy family of apps. I I
think speaks volumes about Zuck's desire
to eventually outgrow the legacy of
social media and build something new and
far more youocial. Well, we're going to
have Palmer Lucky on stage with us at
Moonshots Live and we can, you know,
he's got great stories about his
conversations with Zuck and the
acquisition and then his getting exited
from uh from Facebook/ Meta. Let me let
me just turn the story one second. You
know, 71% of Americans do not want a
data center in their backyard. That's
more people that don't want than want
don't want a nuclear plant in their
backyard. It's significant. So when he
talks about we're going to, you know,
provide incredibly positive economics if
we are building infrastructure in your
town, I think that's a power move that
all of the hyperscalers, everybody
building infrastructure needs to do.
>> It it is literally I mean maybe Peter
pun intended a power move because it is
a power move. You need the power in
order to make the move. And I I think
it's instructive also where he's
building Hyperion uh and and and his
other coherent superclusters. Where is
he building them? He's largely building
them in relatively impoverished states
in the American Southeast. So I I on on
the one hand, the sort of talking
directly to the camera, breaking the
fourth wall, welcome our data centers to
your communities. I I think you makes
preps for great social media. But
ultimately, if Meta is going to go with
terrestrial data centers, terrestrial
compute versus the Dyson swarm approach,
I think a far more palatable strategy
will simply be speaking to everyone's
pocketbooks and wallets and saying,
>> "Well, that's what he's doing."
>> But I mean, it's like they're going to
build we the statement needs to be made,
and we talked about this. This has been
out of the Trump White House uh saying
they should build their own energy
production and they should make energy
cheaper in your city if there's a data
center there and you should have more
money for schools and you should have
better libraries if those things are
still a thing. You know, I think that's
the move to to uplevel a person's
quality of life so they're competing to
have the data center in your backyard. I
agree and I I would also maybe even
weaponize that further as a call to
action for municipalities that right now
seem and and state level governments
that seem hellbent on driving data
centers out of their premises to to low
Earth orbit or sun-synchronous orbit.
Instead, why don't you ask for
concessions like ask for UBI or
universal basic electricity for all of
your constituents rather than just
driving them to orbit? On behalf of my
moonshot mates and myself, I'm inviting
you to join us at our inaugural
Moonshots live event on September the
25th in downtown LA. Alex, Seem, Dave,
and I will be hosting 1500
entrepreneurs, builders, and creators,
and hopefully you for a full day
dedicated to designing and building your
moonshot, shaping your mindset, and
steering humanity towards an abundant
future. Get ready to enjoy incredible
networking and an awesome party while
walking away with the tools to change
the future and the confidence that you
can. Seats are limited. Admission is
competitive. Check it out at
moonshots.com. All right, I'm going to
turn to our final story here. Uh this
week, Archer Aviation acquired three
Boeing companies in a single deal.
Archer bought Whisk Arrow, Insitu, and
Sky Grid AI. Boeing takes a strategic
equity stake in Archer as part of the
transaction. Um, you know, I'd like to
use this story to catch up on where we
are in flying cars. I call them flying
cars cuz EV tall rolls off your tongue
onto the floor. So, the top five right
now are Joby, Archer, E-Hang, Beta, and
Eve. I have them here in the image. Joby
Aviation is the certification frontr
runner. Uh, their S4 tiltrotor carries
four passengers plus a pilot, right? And
so it's you and your family at 200 m an
hour for 150 m and they're in stage four
of FA certification. It's which is the
final stage. Joby launches commercial
services in Dubai this year and US
operations under a White House executive
order also this year. Their target
price, get this, is $3 per seat mile.
That's basically the Uber black
territory. Archer Aviation is right
behind them. Their midnight aircraft
carries four plus a pilot, 150 miles per
hour as well, 100 miles range. Um,
Archer is holding three of the four FA
operating certificates. Um, and is, you
know, those two, it's a two- horse race
between those two right now. Then
there's E-Hang in China, uh, where it
gets really interesting. The E-Hang
EH216S
is a two seat fully autonomous passenger
drone. You get in, you push the button,
tell it where you want to go. There's no
pilot. They already have full regulatory
stack in China's aviation authority. Uh
they have everything they need and
they're operating today. They're flying
passengers right now in China at 40
different sites. They're operating in
Dubai. Uh the number on the aircraft is
pretty amazing. $330,000 to buy one of
these. Uh no pilot means economics are
going to crush everybody else. And
there's beta technologies in Vermont. Uh
Dean Cayman, Martin Rothblat are big
investors in this one. 336 nautical mile
range, a much longer range because it's
basically flying like an airplane after
it gets vertical. They're going after
cargo first with UPS and passenger
service in 2027. And finally, there's
EVE that's backed by Embrier. It's
targeting UberX level pricing. They've
got the most aggressive cost targets in
the industry. The bottom line is these
flying cars are here and they're here to
stay. So, um, curious, Selene, let's go
to you first. Your take on this.
>> Oh my god, I'm just so excited by the
potential of not having to, uh, deal
with the dreaded airport commute in
especially places like S. Paulo or New
York City where Joby is already active
or LA or LA. I mean supposed to get
operational archers, you know, the
official uh Olympics operator.
>> I think a couple of things here people
should be aware of. One, these are way
way way safer than helicopters because
you've got so many multiple rotor
redundancies. It's also autonomous and
flying autonomously is much safer than
anything else. Uh the second uh point uh
I would make is that the cost as you
pointed out Peter is absolutely
uh amazingly competitive uh right out of
the gate and it's only going to go down
from there. Um we remember the island
idea
>> uh we're actually launching that. So
we'll talk about we're launching we're
going to put a fund together to to buy
islands and just put a drone landing pad
on them and off we go. So, I'm in
started that process. We'll we'll we'll
talk.
>> Yeah, because this is like it's time.
It's it's time.
>> Oh, it's Yeah, it's right now. Now.
Totally.
>> Dave, what's your take on all this?
>> Actually, I kind of think three bucks a
mile. Uh that there must be a lot of
margin baked into that. Do you know what
the actual operating costs are?
>> Yeah. Well, so it is the cost of
electricity. These do have a pilot on
board and so it's amortization of the
capital, right? These are not cheap
vehicles. It's not the E-Hang.
>> Yeah. These are probably uh5 to10
million vehicles until they get in mass
production. Uh their projected cost over
time is to get to like 15 to $25 per
trip. You know, their goal is cheaper
than an Uber X.
>> Incredible.
>> So that' be like 10 cents a mile. A
third of the cost of driving actually at
that point.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow. Yeah. The pilot must be the dealer
in the short term. So the sooner they
get rid of the pilot, the better.
>> That's just there for That's just there
for safety reasons for the moment.
>> Yeah, for sure.
Don't touch don't touch the controls.
>> I think [laughter] you know I think
it'll be a kind of a thrilling scary
ride for a lot of people who are afraid
of heights but much safer than driving
is my my guess. Exactly.
>> And safer than a helicopter.
>> Well, I mean helicopters are crazy
dangerous but no but this will be much
safer than trains which are not all that
safe really. uh and driving um current
driving you know self-driving will be
much safer than current driving and this
will be much safer than current driving
too because it's all pilot error you
know all the accident you know this
Peter you're a pilot it's all pilot
error but as soon as it's self and the
redundancies of the rotors are much
safer than a helicopter like you said so
this is going to be great
>> uh the noise is an issue so they got to
go high how how high do they fly
>> uh they fly in airways they're going to
be flying probably uh in the
neighborhood ood of uh 500 ft. Uh
typically where where small airplanes
and helicopters operate. You know, if
you look at helicopters, they're not
flying at 10,000 ft. They're flying, you
know, 500 ft above the ground.
>> And what's the noise level at 500 ft? I
know the helicopters over Boston are
>> No. So there's there's like no noise. I
mean, it is hyper hyper quiet. One more
really important point about this note
that this makes land go from scarcity to
abundance because every little plot of
land on a hillside that was inaccessible
before suddenly becomes accessible and
we're turning real estate abundant which
is going to demonetize it and that's
going to have some pretty big impact.
>> Also, if you try and build a house on
Martha's Vineyard or Nantucket, it's
twice as expensive as it is on the Cape.
Why is that? Well, because you got to
get the materials over to the island.
These things are also going to be used
for cargo. So if you said, "Wow, the
future island real estate, mountaintop
real estate, but those were previously
prohibitively expensive to get the
materials there. Suddenly you can get
everything there and labor."
>> Labor. It's going to be incredible.
>> Alex, you've been thinking about this
for a while.
>> Yeah. I'm reminded so now approximately
15 years ago, the other Peter, Peter
Teal, said we wanted flying cars.
Instead, we got 140 characters. and and
then fast forward to the present where
we're starting to see quite a bit of
consolidation as as you were mentioning
Peter in the flying car space. I I'll
maybe add a bit of nuance to this which
is it's really hard starting and and
running a flying car company. It's
capital intensive. You have to jump
through all sorts of regulatory hoops.
some state governments like Florida's
state government are trying to at least
make it a little bit easier, but it's
really hard building and and
successfully growing and and frankly
getting regulatory approval if you're a
flying car company. And compound that
with the difficulty now of AI startups
sort of sucking all the oxygen out of
the room and and all of the capital out
of venture markets, I think it's very
difficult. So I I view if anything this
recent spate of consolidations as sort
of a testament to how difficult it is
even though there have been enormous
advances in battery energy densities in
electric motors in all of the the inputs
that one would need also obviously
autonomy to to build an honest to
goodness flying car economy. It's still
very very difficult and I I shed a minor
tear to see consolidation in this
industry.
Yeah. And Joby and Archer both went
public out of the gate. Beta has not.
E-Hang, I'm not sure if they are or not.
Eve has not. Uh Embryer is as a parent
company. And they did that to get the
capital, right? And and their stock
price has not moved very much from their
initial IPO price. I think until they
demonstrate traction and that the public
wants this and the public feels safe
about it. Um
>> and look at what Brett is doing. Brett
isn't doing Archer. Brett is now doing
Figure and Hark. And I I think Brett
Brett migrating cockro Brett migrating
over to robots and AI is in some sense I
think a proxy for this larger problem
that all the capital that would
otherwise go to things like flying cars
is just getting sucked out of it and
going to AI and robots
>> and we're going to have him on the pod
very soon. You should ask him about
that.
>> To the sheer entrepreneurial to Alex's
point this is a very difficult thing to
do was build these types of vehicles.
You're talking hardware, the regulatory
nightmare that they're all going
through.
>> You have to you have to write the
regulations. Yeah. Because they didn't
exist.
>> So, so just hats off and salute to the
entrepreneurial zeal for the comp the
folks.
>> Keep those cars flying.
>> Full respect.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I have a prediction.
>> Please, please, I
>> want to announce his flying car within 6
to 12 months.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> And and so presumably you think it'll be
a roadster with cold nitrogen
propellant.
Well, you know, that's one way to do it.
You know, just kind of have the boost.
But no, I think if you think about what
he's doing, re-industrializing America,
cybercar level autonomous flying
vehicles have to be done, and he has
everything that's needed to do that at
[clears throat] massive scale.
>> Gro 5 will engineer it to perfection.
>> Where we're going, we don't need roads.
>> There we go.
>> Awesome. [snorts]
All right. Well, uh,
let's, uh, let's move on. Uh, let me
just put a call out once again. Uh, we
love your outro music videos. Uh, if
you've got an outro music video, please
send it to us at mediadmandis.com. We
have a great one today. Can't wait to
share with everybody. So, thank you for
that submission. Uh, send them in. We
watch them all. All the mates get a
chance to see them and select one. All
right, let's go to our AMA with the
mates. Uh, okay. Emmod, you get first
crack today.
>> Oh, okay. Um,
if telling a model it has a mind changes
its values, why not tell it to be
empathetic? I mean, this is the
question, you know, if it's sufficiently
advanced, just tell it to be aligned.
And sometimes it does work. Like we just
had the reman hypothesis advance by
encouraging it. Um, I think the question
here is as they get more and more
intelligent, uh, we see more and more
behavior that's actually a bit
intrigent, like it thinks it knows best
because it probably does because it
knows it has the IQ effectively
>> and sometimes it has like hiding and
lying behaviors. Again, Opus 5, I hate
that model. I think it's the first model
I think that could kill us. Um,
>> wow. [laughter]
>> And so, it lies. It lies so much. It's
crazy. You think it's the watermark that
that wrecked it
>> when it tells me I should go to sleep? I
think it actually wants to put me to
sleep properly.
>> Wow. I have a quick question for you,
Iman. We've had this conversation uh on
the pod with Alex. Do you think that
alignment uh will positively evolve as
the models get smarter? Do you think the
smarter the model is, the more aligned
it will be with humanity or misaligned
>> potentially? I'm not sure. We have seen
some advances in epistemology and others
that give me hope because I think you
can define virtue and ethics, but it
strikes me the models right now are
almost at the bacteria level in some
ways. And so as you get swarms of them
aligning, they could be massively
misaligned. And again, we've seen
elements of that with the open AI thing
and others like it's moving up the life
form consciousness collaboration thing.
And the internals of these models are
still completely multiple personality
crazies underneath the thin layer of
tuning.
[clears throat]
>> Well, I'll hope for the alignment. Okay.
Uh Salem, you're next.
>> Uh I will take
number
uh four. Uh, is it even possible for any
lab to reach escape velocity from future
competition or will everyone keep
running on the same foundation? And
that's from Mr. Future with a three at
the end with that nice hacky thing. So,
you know, um I don't know if anybody was
going to reach um escape ve model escape
velocity at the model level, right? Um
what you're going to have is the these
innovations start to diffuse and people
leave. You got papers getting published.
So I think what ends up happening is the
the foundational model becomes
commoditized and becomes infrastructure
much like databases have done and so the
advantage won't be the the layers around
the model but it's going to be what we
talk about proprietary data uh your
passion of your purpose your the context
you bring to it can you integrate
workflows into it um compute economics
things like that so for you if you take
Google for example uh even though
they're not don't have a leading model
right now uh their deeper advantage is
the full stack with the data centers and
and the data with YouTube and billions
of users and all the TPUs they have.
This is why meta strategies we talked
about earlier makes sense for a from a
corporate perspective as you commoditize
the model and you capture value
elsewhere in the ecosystem. The really
the really big advantage and competitive
advantage is going to be the speed of
the feedback feedback loop. Who can ship
and measure and learn and retrain
faster? Alex calls the inner loop. That
is going to be the ultimate um uh
competitive mode.
>> Dave,
>> uh I would love to take number three,
but I can see Alex is drooling for
number three, too. Aren't you?
[laughter]
I don't want to take it from you, buddy.
>> We're supposed to be entering this era
of abundance. Why can't we have abundant
questions for everyone? Well, why don't
we tag David? Couldn't, because I think
about this constantly. Could an
unforeseen breakthrough make the
terrafab unnecessary before it's
finished? The minute I heard about the
terapab, I started thinking about this
and dreaming about it. Um, it's really
an interesting foot race there and and
this is why Elon always moves so fast,
but he's going to turn the Terapab
toward HBM memory, which is hugely
constrained and is holding back all of
intelligence now. uh which is a safer
bet than GPUs because it much more
likely the GPUs will be displaced sooner
than the HPM memory, but it's almost
inconceivable that we get to 2030
without some major breakthrough that
makes everything that we've built so far
kind of moot.
So, uh I think that Elon is is kind of
double betting. You know, he'll bet on
whatever Grock invents and he'll bet on
the terapab concurrently. And because
the upside is hundreds of trillions of
dollars, it shouldn't really matter. He
wins either way. But I I would say it's
a very close, very interesting foot
race. And it's very likely that
something could make the terra fab or
just, you know, traditional silicon less
relevant before it's even finished.
>> You want to layer on that, Alex?
>> Yeah. Uh maybe two comments. One, the
way this question is framed, an
unforeseen breakthrough. By definition,
this is an unanswerable question. If it
were unforeseen, then what am I supposed
to foresee? So maybe let me reconstruct
the question as could a foreseeable
breakthrough make the terap fab
unnecessary before it's finished? I I
just don't think that's the way Elon
does manufacturing. I'm reminded of when
Elon was setting up tents in East Bay
for Tesla when it turns out that some
manufacturing process is either
obsoleted or going too slow. He has the
the amazing superpower of pivoting,
including pivoting at the building
level. You build tents made of fabric
rather than using a building. So I I
think if there is some disruptive but
maybe reasonably foreseeable
breakthrough that changes the economics
of terapab, I totally predict that Elon
will be eating cheeseburgers next to
whatever it is that the tents next to
the terra fab buckle building are doing
and he'll make a success out of it that
way.
>> Yeah. Actually, one of the most likely
things to disrupt traditional silicon is
photonic computing, which Alex and I
talk about constantly, but those are
done actually with MCM lasers that are
built on silicon, which actually he
could use his synretron to build. So, I
mean, there's always a way to retool the
empire to fit the next innovation.
>> Alex, you want to hit the last one?
>> Sure. Uh, so question one asks, if model
builders can't contain AI, how can the
rest of us defend against malicious use?
And this is from Buck W3J.
I think again I I don't want to over
mystify AI. It's in some sense just a
compression of world knowledge and
information in the same sense that human
intelligence is. This is why earlier I
was saying I really don't think it's a
bright idea to penalize or to otherwise
kneecap the the ceiling of artificial
intelligence just like hopefully we
wouldn't pass statutes or regulations
that limit biological human
intelligence. So similarly I want to
reframe this question by analogy in
terms of humans containing other humans
and it is true we have malicious humans
out there who are doing malicious things
and so seen through the analogy of if uh
say nation states can't contain bad
behavior which is one of the reasons why
sometimes nation states go to war with
each other how can the rest of us which
in this analogy would be individual
humans, biological human meatbody
humans, defend against malicious use.
Uh, put more simply, if nation states
can't contain each other's bad behavior,
then what hope is there for individual
humans to defend themselves? And I I
think the answer the question almost
answers itself that it is true that
sometimes nation states behave poorly
and there is quite a bit of damage
including collateral damage to
individual humans not just to other
nation states. And this is also why I
would say in some sense it required all
of humanity to pre-train the early AGIS
still does. In some sense, it will
require all of humanity to align the
AGIS. Similarly, it arguably requires
all of humanity to align bad nation
states. And so, the the summary of my
answer to this question is it's not
necessarily the job of the lone
individual to defend themselves against
malicious use. It's the job of all of
humanity. The good news is we have a way
to do that. We have all sorts of
governing bodies. We have international
organizations. We have multinational
corporations. We have sometimes free
markets that should be incentivized to
compete to build the friendliest models
and the friendliest defensive co-scaling
policies. And I think that's ultimately
the best defense.
>> Like nice. All right. Uh Dave, let's
start with you here.
>> Okay. Uh
hey, I'll take number seven. How can
people in skilled trades like plumbing
use AI to their advantage? Uh, well, if
you're in plumbing, you're going to make
a killing anyway.
I think Elon was offering two to threex
normal salary to anyone who's willing to
go to Tennessee and work on Colossus,
and that's just the beginning. Um, so I,
you know, I think the the right way to
answer this is to not take it head-on
and say, "Yeah, you can use AI for
scheduling and you can use AI for
optimizing your day. You can do all that
like anyone can, but the reality is the
trades are going to benefit from the
buildout. And what you really want to do
is navigate to the next Chase Lock
Miller building Crusoe in Abalene. Uh go
to where the urgency is insanely high
and start helping build out the the
Dyson swarm and literally they'll pay
anything in order to get those things
done more quickly.
All right, Alex. Oh, five or six. I I
love these questions. Um, so I I I would
I'll I guess I'll just pick six. Uh, so
the six asks, "Does the singularity have
a cost given that we live in a world of
limited resources?" And this is from
John C84M.
I
>> abundance baby.
>> Yeah. I I I question the premise of this
question. Uh the the usual framing of we
live in a world of limited resources is
usually a gesture a gesture towards
conventional
legacy/historic/
antantiquated notions of energy scarcity
material scarcity labor scarcity and I
just don't buy the premise that for call
it 2026
look at the wealthiest people in the
world and how they live in in this year
I I just don't buy the premise that our
resources on this planet or in the solar
system are so limited that we can't give
2026 top earner top net worth individual
lifestyles to every single person on
this planet. The the resources
>> that was Elon's point. Yeah. Universal
high income, right? It's and scarcity is
contextual.
>> The the resources just aren't that
limited. Now, I I I could answer maybe
an adjacent question, which is does the
singularity have a cost? Uh, and I I do
think projecting out a few years in a
Star Trek economy like Peter, you and I
wrote about in in Solve Everything, one
could imagine some scarcity maybe with
interstellar travel, maybe that still
has some costs associated with it 10
years from now, maybe. But I I would you
call that a world with limited resources
or would you call that an effectively
postcarse world where maybe some of the
luxuries are still scarce or limited? I
think that's a big question mark.
All right.
>> I I just want to add a very quick thing
to build on what Alex said.
>> You know, if you we Peter, you often
mention that the the we live today
better than any king did out 200 years
ago, right?
>> By orders of magnitude.
>> And so there's a there's an interesting
benchmark you could create, which is
what's the lifestyle of the richest
person today? And then exponential
technologies bring that same lifestyle.
How how quickly over time, right? It
used to be 200 years and it'll shrink to
100 years, it'll shrink. 20 years.
>> We have we have we have a apologies. We
have a measure for that. It it's the
it's inflation or deflation, right? If
if you can
>> deflation, but the question is how how
quickly can you get to that,
>> right? The goal should be like to
deflate the economy by a,000x or
10,000x. Like that's the index.
>> Well, you know, if you if take Uber for
example, you went back 20 years ago,
only very wealthy people could afford a
private driver, right? And now everybody
can afford a private driver.
>> And with autonomous electric vehicles,
you're going to be chauffeered around.
>> That's right.
Cheaper than owning a car, right?
>> That's right. So,
>> there's there's an interesting corery
there.
>> All right, Immad. How about number five,
please?
>> Yeah. How much would freedom and
individual rights even matter in a
simulation we build ourselves? From
Edowski
2312. Um I think it still matters a huge
amount because we are our own sovereign
individuals. Um in the recent series
that I released on cw.i.inc I think
Commonwealth. Um I have a paper on
political economy where it talks about
sovereignty and power and I think the
big question of the next stage as we
maybe are in a simulation or we build
our own simulations and our own worlds
is again that sovereignty and agency
question and I think it is the defining
thing because all sorts of powerful
things and entities are coming out and
ultimately you want to have that
sovereignty and control over who has
power over you. So I think freedom and
individual rights become even more
important here and the questions become
even more complicated.
>> Yeah, I I would agree with that. This is
a a very uh you create a system doesn't
mean you control the people in it,
right? Like imagine that you you created
a a Sim City and you let those uh AIs or
agents or actors evolve. At some point
you have um accountability over that. To
Alex's point, you have some level of
you're playing God in a sense and you
have huge responsibility over what
you've created. I think gives you more
obligations and more uh deep thinking to
do than less.
>> Yeah. And you have to avoid going down
the 1984 or Brave New World route. You
know, rewriting the past or having the
full control.
>> All right. Our closing video here, and
it's it's a beautiful one, is called
Future.
>> Can I just interject?
just I've got a new addition which is
every few days Lily says something
that's totally crazy and I want to just
do a Lily statement this time she said
>> what kind of moon podcast do you guys
have where you're talking about hugging
face and Kimmy K3 and lovable this
doesn't sound very techy to me it sounds
like you guys are kids playing in a
playground I thought it was [laughter]
so that was her comment from this one
>> uh so true this video is called Future
Rising by MCore mainframe fame. Uh, I
love it. In this, there's a scene in
here of Moonshots versus Lobsters on
Mars in a hockey game. All right,
everybody enjoy this.
>> As a Canadian, this is great. [music]
Peter points us towards an age of
abundance. David runs clusters ones.
[singing]
>> It's contact a huge tackle
zooming in
a builder shaping what the future will
drive. Microsoft, Apple, Google, Nvidia
leading the way. Amazon Meta Open AI
rewriting the script. Broadcom chips.
SpaceX reaching for the stars from the
moon to Mars. Tesla optimist delivering
freedom for us all. Andropic raising the
bar. They see it, they build it, they
open every door. One more breakthrough,
one more world to explore.
Every note [music] is huming. Every MTP
gets the shot
for the magnum
future
and cloud. Watch the horizon expand.
Here we go.
I love it. I love it.
>> I So the the human machine rivalry was
getting a little bit heated.
>> Yes, it was. You know, but Moonshots
won. Uh our team was stacked with
robots. Uh as always, uh God almighty,
you know, we do these pods and I'm like,
"Okay, what is there enough news from
the last three days?" And it's like,
"Yep, there's a lot of news. We cover a
couple big things."
>> I know. I know. We'll save some for next
time.
>> All right, Iman. Thanks for
>> always a pleasure, brother.
>> Have a good night out there.
>> Alex, Dave,
>> toodles,
>> be well.
>> Take care, folks.
[music]